<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Love's posie: or, A collection of seven and twenty love-letters, both in verse and prose; that lately pass'd betwixt a gentleman and a very young lady in France.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04227</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829009</idno>
  <idno type="VID">179501</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248495625</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217332</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829009</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04227)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179501)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1972:1, 2790:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Love's posie: or, A collection of seven and twenty love-letters, both in verse and prose; that lately pass'd betwixt a gentleman and a very young lady in France.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 153, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Joseph Hindmarsh, at the Golden Ball near the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partially in verse.</note>
                  <note>Title within double-line border.</note>
                  <note>With a final page of errata.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1972:1 and 2790:33.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: copy at reel 1972:1 lacking pp.112-115; copy at reel 2790:33 stained with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Love poetry --  Early modern, 1500-1700.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Love-letters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Love's Posie:</hi> OR, A COLLECTION OF <hi>Seven</hi> and <hi>Twenty</hi> LOVE-LETTERS, BOTH IN <hi>VERSE</hi> and <hi>PROSE;</hi> That lately pass'd betwixt a GENTLEMAN <hi>and a very Young</hi> LADY <hi>in</hi> FRANCE.</p>
            <q>Nescio, quid Melius Desidiosus agas. <bibl>
                  <hi>Mart.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joseph Hindmarsh,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1686.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:2"/>
            <head>
               <add>A PLEADER TO THE NEEDER WHEN A READER.</add>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <add>AS all, my friend, through wily knaves, full often suffer wrongs,</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>Forget not, pray, when it you've read, to whom this book belongs.</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>Than one Charles Clark, of Totham Hall, none to't a right hath better,</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>A <hi>wight,</hi> that same, more <hi>read</hi> than some in the lore of old <hi>black</hi>-letter.</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>And as C. C. in <hi>Essex</hi> dwells—a shire at which all laugh—</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>His books must, sure, less fit seem drest, if they're not bound in <hi>calf!</hi>
                  </add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>Care take, my friend, this book you ne'er with grease or dirt besmear it;</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>While none but awkward <hi>puppies</hi> will continue to <hi>"dog's</hi>-ear" it!</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>And o'er my books when book-<hi>worms "grub,"</hi> I'd have them understand,</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>No marks the margins must de-<hi>face</hi> from any busy <hi>"hand!"</hi>
                  </add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>Marks, as re-marks, in books of Clark's, when e're some critic spy leaves,</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>It always him so <hi>wasp</hi>-ish makes, though they're but on the <hi>fly</hi>-leaves!</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>Yes, if so they're used, he'd not de-<hi>fer</hi> to <hi>deal</hi> a fate most meet—</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>He'd have the soiler of his <hi>qu'res</hi> do penance in a <hi>sheet!</hi>
                  </add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>The Ettrick <hi>Hogg</hi>—ne'er deemed a <hi>bore</hi>—his candid mind revealing,</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>Declares, to beg "a <hi>copy"</hi> now's a mere pre-<hi>text</hi> for stealing!</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>So, as some knave to grant the loan of this my book may wish me,</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>I thus my book-<hi>plate</hi> here display, lest some such "fry" should <hi>dish</hi> me!</add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>—But hold,—though I again declare WITH-holding I'll not <hi>brook,</hi>
                  </add>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <add>And "a <hi>sea</hi> of trouble" still shall take to bring book-worms "to <hi>book!"</hi>
                  </add>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:7"/>
            <head>Programma Interpretis AD Libellum.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>QƲIN jam, Blandule, sive tu Libelli,</l>
               <l>Sen Nati titulo velis vocari,</l>
               <l>Exi jam Gremio, proterve, nostro.</l>
               <l>Satis de Genibus tener Paternis</l>
               <l>Risisti: Satis insolente circum</l>
               <l>Lusisti patrios manu Capillos;</l>
               <l>Quòd vel laetior adfuit <hi>Camoena,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vel Rhythmum malè vindicavit unguis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nee jàm respue <hi>Filii Popelli</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nomen: Abdico te tuosque mores.</l>
               <l>Tu forsan Populo placere juxtà</l>
               <l>Focos <hi>Idalios</hi> potes sedenti,</l>
               <l>Qui cunctam <hi>Veneris</hi> sacrae Favillam</l>
               <l>In magnas solet aggravare Flammas,</l>
               <l>Istas, Improbe, quas merere Flammas.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:179501:9"/>
               <l>Quid dixi? Improbulo tibi nec Ignes</l>
               <l>Insani <hi>Venerum Cupidinumque,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nec insunt <hi>Aloysiae</hi> Camini.</l>
               <l>At <hi>Vestae Venus</hi> est tibi Sacerdos,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vestales</hi> refovens Amoris ignes,</l>
               <l>Corde hinc <hi>Iridos,</hi> indè vel <hi>Timandri.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O quae gaudia pura spirat <hi>Ille!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O quae gaudia pura spirat <hi>Illa!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Quàm molles animi subit Ille poenas,</l>
               <l>Quas quàm callida discit Illa lentas!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Exi, Blandule: Nunc utrasque narra:</l>
               <l>Et cùm nil nisi contines Amorem,</l>
               <l>Lectoris tibi quaere sis Amorem.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179501:9"/>
            <head>The Introductory LETTER, TO THE <hi>Right Honourable, the Lady</hi> D.</head>
            <q>YOU command me, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> to send you the Letters of <hi>the young Iris,</hi> together with my own. The last I cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to refuse you, because I am master of them; and the others you have honour'd with so much esteem, that it will be ever reputed glorious to the young <hi>Iris,</hi> to have gotten so Illustrioius a suffrage as yours,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179501:10"/>in her Favour. 'Tis true, towards the inducing me to put into your hands those Letters, of which she wou'd have me make an eternal Mystery, you have taken me by the weaker side; you have given them Praises so complemental, <hi>Madam,</hi> and yet so just, that tho I had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd to conceal them from all the rest of the World, you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain me now to put 'em forth to the open view; so sweet and taking a thing is it, to hear that valued which we love, especially by a Person of your incomparable Merits, whose Wit is so sharp and delicate, that I cannot bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reward this esteem than by the thing it self. You will see here an Intrigue, that began perfectly out of meer sport and pastime, but terminated on my part only with the conquest of my Heart, without disturbing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179501:10"/>that most lovely Creature's, who made but too good a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, for my repose. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, <hi>Madam,</hi> is not much to my Honour: But however, it is not inglorious for a Man to make an open acknowledgment, <hi>That</hi> he loves that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves to be belov'd. Six whole Months as well counted, as ever the Calendar counted them, I have spun out in sincere and hearty Love; this every Man in the World wou'd not have done. And, tho <hi>Celadon</hi> (who is dead and gone) nor his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample be very modish in the Age, wherein we live, I have met with a certain sort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that have made me tread in his steps; and, my heart as free and ill-principl'd as it is, could not keep from assuming somewhat more Tenderness than Reason, for a young Thing, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179501:11"/>had none at all. I mean Tenderness; since of Reason she had an infinite deal, as you have seen by her Letters. You have an huge mind to know her, and you desire her Picture of me. I question, whether I have Abilities sufficient to draw a faithful Image of her: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless, I will do it without any Adulation, and any manner of Addition, or to the Lines of her Visage, or those of her Mind.</q>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Portraiture</hi> of <hi>Iris.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The turn of her Face is Oval; her Complexion fair and even; the Trammels of her Hair of an admirable Light colour, as well as her Eye brows. Excellently well proportion'd is her Nose, which gives a very fine Air to the Face: Her Mouth, neither too great nor too little; her Lips of a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179501:11"/>clear and beautiful Red; her Teeth white; her Eyes blew, great, and well-passag'd, full of fire and brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, temper'd with an attractive lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing: And, all this is support<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the coolness of a Neck of sixteen years, the best fram'd that ever was seen, and of a dazling whiteness, as well as her Arms and Hands. For her Stature, she is rather of a great than little pitch, almost approaching to a <hi>Roman</hi> Empress; but then, it is so neat, so free, so disengag'd, that there are few the like. She hath so no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an Air in her Walk and her Carriage, and something so very distinguishing in her whole Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; that, tho she possesses not some strokes that are delightful, yet she has such as make great Impressions: So that, tho we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not say, she is of the member of those Beauties, that jump at, and smite the Eyes, yet we may easily
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179501:12"/>perceive, that hers goeth straight to the Heart. But above all, she has an odd sort of pretty Air, which is very difficult to be describ'd, and seems rather to catch us, than we can tell, how to overtake it.</p>
               <l>A <hi>certain careless</hi> sliding Air</l>
               <l>Draws us <hi>aright</hi> her <hi>Character:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>all</hi> their piercing <hi>Light</hi> her <hi>Eyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>[<hi>Such</hi> as is <hi>shot</hi> from <hi>Morning</hi> skies;]</l>
               <l>Would <hi>speak</hi> in <hi>earnest:</hi> But, <hi>alass!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her <hi>Heart, insensible,</hi> doth pass</l>
               <l>On them a <hi>Tyrannous</hi> strict <hi>Command,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Night</hi>'s dark <hi>silence</hi> wrapt to <hi>stand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But still, much <hi>Trouble</hi> they <hi>sustain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In doing <hi>this,</hi> nor can <hi>refrain,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:179501:12"/>
               <l>For all their high <hi>Indifference,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>speak</hi> a <hi>Language</hi> in <hi>such</hi> sence,</l>
               <l>As doth not <hi>look</hi> like <hi>Indolence.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If only her sweet <hi>Mouth</hi> obeys,</l>
               <l>To make a <hi>fair amends,</hi> she <hi>says</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>More</hi> in this <hi>swimming Air,</hi> than <hi>we</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can <hi>think,</hi> and <hi>thinks</hi> more than we <hi>see.</hi>
               </l>
               <p>"This is what I had to say con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning her Person. As to her Wit, it has so strangely surpriz'd me, that I am hardly yet come to my self. I cou'd not comprehend, how a young Person between Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen and Sixteen, without Study and the World; could have, in the furthermost Corner of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, all the Politeness of a Court, an inconceiveable Flame and strength of mind, an un-parallel'd delicacy and penetration, a most pure, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecate and subtile discernment. Of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179501:13"/>every thing, she speaks so well and so justly, without any Fore-learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; that Nature seems to have made a largess to her, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a long Study and Meditation doles out by degrees to others. Her terms, very proper and accurately chosen; her thoughts, so new, so particular, that they raise our Astonishment and Admiration. A scanty reading hath serv'd her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of all the expedients used by others: An immense Fund of Wit, a most lively Imagination, and a sharp sighted and nice Judgment, these compleat her Character Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, she has such sallies in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, as it is impossible to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. She takes a singular pleasure in holding Paradoxes, and with great facility she commonly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains her end. She writes, as you have seen, that is to say, with an inchanted daintiness. She compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth Verses so easily, and winds 'em
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179501:13"/>so well, that nothing can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd better. Her Prose is clever and adequate; her thoughts all Originals; concise her Style; her expressions Noble and Great: All which is accompanied with a Fashion and a Character, that is wholly peculiar, and gives the grace and relish to every thing. From others she borrows nothing, but only imitates her self. For her Soul, it is large, good, and generous; very kind to its Friend, but very unkind to its Lover. Its humor is unequal enough of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; and this is the shadow to the Picture. This inequality arises from the over-great Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of fire in her mind. As to her Heart, with its Appendages, I can say nothing to it: It is now three years I have been Studying it, and yet I am not acquainted with it. However, it talks, as if it knew very much; but yet it sighs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179501:14"/>no more, than if it was the meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Ignorant in the World. It is as curious, as her Wit: And, if it had but somewhat more tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, I think, I may say upon the word of an honest Man, it wou'd be indisputably the loveliest Heart upon Earth. Notwithstanding which, tho it defends it self, I believe its disposition naturally tender enough: (the true disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Heart, well descended;) But it guards it self with so much care, that frequently we know not what to believe. However, we meet with a Passion every where dispersed in her Writings, which appears inimitable; and doubtless, if her Heart has none, yet, her Wit gives very many, and very evident Demonstrations of it.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:179501:14"/>
               <l>If we <hi>view</hi> Lovely <hi>Iris</hi> with <hi>nice</hi> Eyes,</l>
               <l>Or her <hi>Heart</hi> reasons, or her <hi>Reason</hi> sighs:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sometimes,</hi> we might <hi>believe</hi> her <hi>real Love;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But that <hi>suspicion</hi> soon <hi>despair</hi> does prove.</l>
               <l>Seeing her <hi>Austere</hi> humor, it <hi>retires;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And with our <hi>frailty</hi> if her <hi>Eye</hi> conspires</l>
               <l>In the <hi>dire Treason,</hi> we must needs <hi>confess</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From a <hi>fierce Glance,</hi> that her <hi>Heart</hi> hath no <hi>less</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Reason,</hi> than her <hi>Reason Tenderness.</hi>
               </l>
               <q>This is, <hi>Madam,</hi> the Pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture of the young <hi>Iris:</hi> I have drawn it coarsely and ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>favour'dly; to Love it belongs to put the last hand to it. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided he replenishes her Heart
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179501:15"/>with a true Passion as he has fill'd mine, I shall not be unhappy; and since she is unwilling to be sensible of any tenderness, but in Draught and Picture, such as you see it in her
<note n="*" place="margin">18, &amp; 19.</note> Letters; all that I wish</q>
               <l>Is, that her <hi>tenderness</hi> in <hi>draught,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of such a <hi>Nature</hi> may be <hi>wrought;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As <hi>Love</hi> frames, not to be <hi>effac'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By <hi>time,</hi> but with the <hi>Soul</hi> to <hi>last.</hi>
               </l>
               <q>This is the Representation of her Person: But in good truth, I have taken so much pleasure in writing to her, and receiving her Letters; and, these have rais'd so much Admiration in every thing at Court, that is Judging, delicate, and curious, that I have made my self as many Rivals, as I had Auditors of these stupendous Letters. You
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179501:15"/>know it very well, <hi>Madam,</hi> (and this is it, that hath contributed to my undoing:) Such Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are there in hearing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where the Encomiums of such Persons, with whom our Hearts are pre possess'd, and this way a Man does so throughly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand their Worth, that he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly abandons himself to his own Inclination. It is very happy for me, that she continues still in the Country; For, otherwise, I should have here such Rivals of Blood and Merit, as without contradiction wou'd make me tremble, if my self had not at least the advantage of places I that are almost accessible to the most Worshipful of my Fellow Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates. The young <hi>Iris</hi> has chid me extremely for my indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion in shewing her Letters, which she looks upon only as a piece of Sport and Recreation.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179501:16"/>Her. I satisfy'd with such good Reasons, as I shall not repeat in this place. It behoved me indeed to keep them private, since my Passion was disappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and came so scurvily off: But, her Glory I have preferr'd before my own; and, I fancy, she ought not to be ungrateful to me, for taking care, that the superlative Products of her Wit and Pen be recommended to the admiration of a Party, the most clear headed in <hi>France,</hi> who have stood amaz'd at her. I have plac'd her Letters in the same order I received them: And, as I have had but very few sights of her, and have tarried but very little in the Province, where she makes her abode; I have rang'd them in their natural or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, according to the times they were sent me. I have now and then made some Remarks and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179501:16"/>Annotations, by unfolding the Subject-matter of some of 'em, and hinting the different Models of the Verses, so that you might have the clearer Ideas of their Beauty. Thus, <hi>Madam,</hi> I have endeavour'd to obey you with all the exactness, so much due to you, and to render a faithful account of all the Circumstances belonging to an innocent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, of which the young <hi>Iris</hi> bore away all the glory. But, if hereby, I create any trouble to <hi>Iris,</hi> I hope, <hi>Madam,</hi> you will be responsible for it: Yet, what ever happen, I beg of you to believe, that with the most profound Respect I shall ever be,</q>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:179501:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi> to the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The First Letter.</head>
            <p>DO you remember, that you took me yesterday at my Word? That you accepted of me for your Master, and that you are my Scholar? And, in short, do you remember, That you are to put into my hands the loveliest Heart in the World, to be instructed in the most diverting Passion, that can be imagin'd? For my share, I stand in no need of having my Memory refresh'd, that I have seen you, or concerning the Promise I made you: And besides, I feel my self very much dispos'd to make it good, Undoubtedly, there will be a vast deal of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in documentizing such an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179501:17"/>Simpleton: But I foresee, it will not be without trouble. If I have any skill in Physiognomy, you look as if your Heart was harder than your Head: But, 'tis no matter, I must be always in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcating a Lesson of Tenderness.</p>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>To <hi>teach</hi> you, what I <hi>know</hi> too <hi>well,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For me an <hi>easie Chapter</hi> it will be:</l>
               <l>And You, tho <hi>you</hi> could only <hi>spell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May <hi>read</hi> and <hi>Practise</hi> the <hi>Lines</hi> after <hi>me.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>One <hi>Blessed weakness</hi> in us <hi>both,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>both</hi> must the same <hi>fears</hi> breath and <hi>desires:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And least I be <hi>accus'd</hi> of <hi>floath,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your <hi>Gleams</hi> upon me I'll encrease to <hi>fires.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:179501:18"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>And <hi>presently</hi> to learn your <hi>part,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Most <hi>constant</hi> at my <hi>Lessons</hi> you must <hi>be:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And if you <hi>get</hi> them <hi>once</hi> by <hi>heart,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I'll fix <hi>them</hi> and <hi>my self</hi> safe in your Memory.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>This is enough for the first time, my pretty Ignorance; and if you make good Progress in these three Lessons, you will soon know as much as your Master, if not put him quite down.</p>
            <l>But, what? <hi>methinks,</hi> you have the <hi>mien</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of a <hi>Disciple</hi> truly <hi>Libertine:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And in your <hi>Eyes</hi> I plainly <hi>see.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Your reatchless <hi>Heart</hi> will a meer <hi>Truant</hi> be;</l>
            <l>Your <hi>Heart</hi> will take its own <hi>wild swing</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In spight of <hi>Master, Lesson — Any thing.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:179501:18"/>
            <p>However, if you desire to make something of the business, proceed in such wise, as not to let your Wit intermeddle with the Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations of your Heart: For, that is too sly and searching, to enter into Correspondence with me.</p>
            <l>Yes, tho to <hi>me</hi> this <hi>Wit</hi> be all o'er <hi>Charm,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Let it not <hi>tamper</hi> with <hi>hid Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For, in <hi>Love,</hi> where <hi>all</hi> above <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> flies,</l>
            <l>Reason, <hi>as in</hi> Religion, <hi>doth much</hi> Harm.</l>
            <p>If you follow these Maxims, I make no doubt, but you will be notable good at Passion in a little time. Consult your own Heart young <hi>Iris,</hi> and ask it, whether it wou'd prefer its Ignorance, which is a true state of Lethargy, to a Science, from which it might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179501:19"/>a thousand Pleasures. I am certain, if it knew the sweetness, there is, in loving something, and the delights of a true amorous Association, it wou'd no longer remain in this Error, but you wou'd one day repeat to your self the burthen of <hi>Galathea</hi>'s Song, which I sung to you yesterday.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To know all, is good,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>How happy shou'd I be, if I cou'd speak to you almost in the same Air!</p>
            <l>One day the <hi>Heart</hi> of a <hi>bright Creature,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>(Whose every <hi>thought,</hi> and every <hi>Feature</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Would <hi>adverse</hi> Elements <hi>inspire,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And even teach <hi>Water</hi> to love <hi>Fire)</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of a <hi>learn'd Master</hi> did approve,</l>
            <l>T' <hi>instruct</hi> her in the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Love:</hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:179501:19"/>
            <l>Though all the <hi>Light,</hi> he had i'th' <hi>same,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Was <hi>drawn</hi> (as some think) from her <hi>flame.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>This <hi>Master</hi> through his <hi>Tenderness,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Which he <hi>declar'd</hi> in his <hi>Address,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Made her <hi>repeat</hi> incessantly;</l>
            <l>How <hi>sweet</hi> it is to <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>sigh,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>How <hi>sweet</hi> it is, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </l>
            <q>This, <hi>Madam,</hi> was the first of my Love-Epistles, that I wrote to her. She wou'd by no means answer it: That sole Proposition of establishing a mutual and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Intelligence spoil'd all, and affrighted the young Maiden. I endeavour'd to remove these difficulties, which were not over-bulkly. I gave her to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that such an affair wou'd be of great service to fashion her Wit, to give it an agreeable shape, and it wou'd only prove an innocent and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179501:20"/>harmless amusement, that cou'd have no such staggering conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. In brief, after many Arguments and Instances, I prevail'd with her to resolve to make me a reply, which was this: It begins with that Copy of Verses, you have already commended, for the pretty Country-sonnettism in them, which runs very neatly upon one word, tho the measures of the Verse be Irregular.</q>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="letter">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:179501:20"/>
            <head>
               <hi>IRIS,</hi> her Answer to <hi>TIMANDER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Second Letter.</head>
            <l>WEll, well, <hi>Timander!</hi> 'twixt us <hi>two,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To <hi>hear</hi> a Lover,'s <hi>much</hi> for a <hi>young Maid:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of un <hi>Intrigue</hi> the <hi>Ground work</hi> will be <hi>laid;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And then, what shall I <hi>do,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Or will you <hi>think</hi> of such a <hi>fond</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,</l>
            <l>So very <hi>tender,</hi> and <hi>impertinent?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>No,</hi> the affair is <hi>such;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The least <hi>Engagement</hi> is a <hi>willing</hi> Ear,</l>
            <l>And to take <hi>well,</hi> what's <hi>heard,</hi> I fear</l>
            <l>Is too <hi>too much.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:179501:21"/>
            <l>I see the <hi>danger,</hi> and th' <hi>event</hi> I dread:</l>
            <l>But tho I don't much <hi>care</hi> to run into it,</l>
            <l>Out of pure <hi>Self-defence</hi> I'll do it,</l>
            <l>And <hi>shew,</hi> my <hi>Heart</hi> cannot be <hi>Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quished.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But now, at <hi>first,</hi> if it <hi>should</hi> prove a <hi>Cheat,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>It should be <hi>much,</hi> it would be a <hi>strange Feat.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Seriously, I know not, whether I deceive my self: But methinks, it is for the pleasure of defending my own Heart, that I consent, you shou'd attack it. I cannot war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for its stoutness, upon the Faith of its past senslesness. As never Man did yet attempt upon its peace and quiet; 'tis no wonder, if it has hitherto preserv'd its Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity: And it is now a fit time, to put it to the Tryal, at least to know, what Mettal it is made of. This couriosity of mine
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:179501:21"/>is something audacious, and I may thence fall into inconveniences: But, in a word, I believe, it comes to the same thing, once to have lost it, or to be evermore afraid of losing it, and to put it to no manner of use at all. The uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, I should lye under, by not knowing, whether it be Tenable or defenceless, wou'd be an eternal Thorn in my side. Now this is the utmost Passion it self can do: And laying one Trouble in ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance against another, I prefer that which hath the Reputation of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the most pleasurable. Upon the whole, it is not undone by a venture: I may be able to retire back with Honour. My Heart (God be prais'd) springs from a Race, wherein sighs have not been much used: And, I hope, it will not degenerate from the Antient indifference of its Predecessors. I took it t'other day aside in private,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179501:22"/>and I read a severe Lecture to it: I strictly charged it not to play with Love, since</p>
            <l>For all the <hi>Apish tricks,</hi> which <hi>Love</hi> does <hi>play</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With <hi>those</hi> that <hi>go</hi> to his <hi>Free-School,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yet to their <hi>serious cost</hi> they <hi>find</hi> one day,</l>
            <l>There is no <hi>jesting</hi> with the <hi>Fool.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>It has promis'd me faithfully to obey my Orders, and to make grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter use of my Lessons than of yours. After this, I imagin my self in a condition good enough, to send you a defiance: All your tendernesses and all your Assiduities may do their worst; chuse, whether you will continue them or no. The glory lies equal between us, you to make a Conquest of me, and I of you, without any self-engagement. Let us try, who shall get the Honour:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179501:22"/>To the intent, at least, that the Scholar may always remain Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris of her Master.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi>'s Answer to the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Third Letter.</head>
            <p>YOU have so much Wit, that you are ready to make me lose that pittance I have left. To that degree, I am surpriz'd at the vivacity, I found in your <hi>Billet,</hi> that I know not, where I am. What an Impression have you made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Heart? I am mad both at you, and at my self; at you, for finding so much in you; at my self, for finding my self so sensible of it. 'Tis plain, such a Scholar as you, knows more than such a Master as I am; and this hath
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:179501:23"/>astonish'd me, at your Age. But to answer your Letter: If you tast not the pleasure of that charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perplexity, which is fam'd for being the most diverting, all your Life will be pester'd with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference, that will weigh you down some time or other. You are to risk your Heart, only to loose it: And if you would come off with Honour, pursue these dictates.</p>
            <l>What does the lovely <hi>Iris</hi> mean to <hi>do?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>All <hi>armed</hi> Rigour must be <hi>laid</hi> aside;</l>
            <l>Her Heart <hi>un-garisson'd</hi> must <hi>abide,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When it <hi>lets in</hi> a Man to <hi>Woo.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>Love</hi> are no <hi>Alarms,</hi> but <hi>all</hi> is <hi>Tame,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And, to <hi>come off</hi> with <hi>Honour,</hi> is a <hi>shame.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Wherefore, do not any longer brag of the hardness of your Heart, nor of the un-common use of sighs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179501:23"/>among the Gentlemen, your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors: For, I can convince you in two words, of the contrary.</p>
            <l>Your <hi>Family,</hi> for <hi>Beauties</hi> so <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Degenerate</hi> wou'd have been <hi>sound:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And, had not your <hi>Fore-mothers</hi> lov'd and <hi>sigh'd,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Iris</hi> had been to th' World <hi>deny'd:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>I</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> might e'en <hi>sigh</hi> out our <hi>Hearts,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For <hi>want</hi> of <hi>one</hi> of its most <hi>perfect Parts.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Strive to repair their Honour, with all the hast you can: Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, follow their eminent and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Examples, and ever let some Love enter into your heart in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of better times; it will exercise it so prettily, that, I am confident, you will not be unsatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd with it.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:179501:24"/>
            <l>
               <hi>Bear</hi> with the <hi>Foppish tricks</hi> of that <hi>fond Boy,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Since 'tis <hi>all</hi> only <hi>ductile</hi> Rallery:</l>
            <l>And if <hi>sometimes</hi> there succeed some <hi>Annoy,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>'Tis, as when after <hi>Laughing</hi> much we <hi>Cry.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>For, in conclusion, what can you propound to your self from Conquering me, unless I get a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory too, in my Turn?</p>
            <l>Ah <hi>Barbarous,</hi> me <hi>thus</hi> to <hi>use,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And ev'n an <hi>intire</hi> thraldom to <hi>refuse!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To <hi>tarnish</hi> with your <hi>Cruelty,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>An <hi>half got</hi> Victory,</l>
            <l>Tho at your <hi>Feet</hi> the <hi>Prostrate</hi> slave do lye!</l>
            <l>For, the <hi>whole Conquest</hi> is <hi>again</hi> to <hi>do;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Ʋnless the <hi>Conqueror</hi> be <hi>Conquer'd</hi> too.</l>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:179501:24"/>
            <q>Some time after the delivery of this Answer, I continued without seeing her; but it was not without much Affliction and inquietude. I was forward to seek all occasions of meeting her, but in vain. I was twenty times with a Friend of hers, but could not find her: At length, after fifteen days, whose Minutes I was very industrious to reckon, I providentially fell into her Company. On her side, the Conversation was active, brisk and airy, but somewhat heavy and cumbersom on mine. As I was dampt in Spirit, I diverted the discourse to a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver's disorder, when he wou'd speak, but can find no words proper enough, wherein to utter his mind. At this, she sell a blushing, and had some confusion upon her: Her Letter coming into her mind, where she speaks
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179501:25"/>of that intricating Trouble, which hath the credit of being the most pleasant of all others. I meditated some revenge upon her: And in a laughing way, shewing her the disorder wherein she was, this increas'd it as much again. She, then, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to me far more lovely than ever: I told her, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching Redness, that had made her so beautiful, did deserve some Verses very well. She forbad me to make any: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the next day, I gave her the ensuing Note.</q>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="letter">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:179501:25"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi> to the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Fourth Letter.</head>
            <p>WHat a sensible joy did the sight of you yesterday afford me! Fifteen days had gone over our heads, while I sought you every where, without finding you: And, all this time, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, you never dreamt one moment of me. You look'd more lovely, than ever; In the same instant, your Eyes told me an hundred pretty things as well as your Mouth: With what emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions did I see 'em? With what pleasure did I hear you, that short time we were together? But alas! I partook only of this pleasure; and had it not been for that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable blush, that came in to my
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179501:26"/>Aid, in my revenge upon your indifference. I know not what I shou'd have done. Your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity help'd somewhat to dissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate mine: And, notwithstanding the Prohibition, you have given me,</p>
            <l>I must <hi>remember</hi> to my <hi>Praise,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>I did your <hi>blushes,</hi> my own <hi>Trophies,</hi> raise:</l>
            <l>Which, when, <hi>Fair Shepherdess,</hi> you <hi>call</hi> to <hi>mind,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>You</hi> at your <hi>blushes</hi> will be so <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To <hi>say,</hi> that from <hi>displeasure</hi> they arose:</l>
            <l>But I have th' <hi>Wit,</hi> a better source to choose:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Love,</hi> and not <hi>Indignation</hi> let them <hi>loose.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Now, will I lay a Wager, at this very moment you are most furiously angry at me, and you
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179501:26"/>Colour again, while you read these Verses. Take your Glass quickly into your hands, I conjure you: See, how lovely you appear, and what an over-plus of Beauty an high Colour gives you! Well, I am sure, you will thank me, in private, for having made you blush.</p>
            <l>When those <hi>piercing</hi> Eyes we <hi>view,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Divinely <hi>languishing</hi> in you;</l>
            <l>When a <hi>Crescent Redness</hi> seeks</l>
            <l>A <hi>Seat Triumphant</hi> in your <hi>Cheeks:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Then <hi>know,</hi> that <hi>Love</hi> plays <hi>there</hi> his <hi>Part,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Blushing,</hi> he <hi>cannot</hi> get <hi>into</hi> your <hi>Heart.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>So, so! have not I given an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent solution of your Reddening? Do not, therefore, any more arm your self at all points against me: Do but take away the very cause of this Redness, in regard it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds only from your shutting the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179501:27"/>entrance of your Heart to Love, so that he is constrain'd to fly up into your Face.</p>
            <l>Thus, <hi>Brightest Form,</hi> let all your <hi>Anger</hi> go,</l>
            <l>And <hi>blush</hi> not in <hi>Repentance,</hi> that you have <hi>blusht</hi> so.</l>
            <p>I hope, by this time I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd your Pardon. What you told me, yesterday, concerning the Interruption of our Correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency did not displease me: And, forasmuch as I have not the liberty to see you, at least let me have that of writing to you: But, principally,</p>
            <l>
               <hi>Sweetness,</hi> take <hi>Argus</hi> heed of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidents;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Always they <hi>want</hi> or <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Sense.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:179501:27"/>
            <l>Let the <hi>great secret</hi> still be <hi>such unknown,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And as 'tis <hi>ours,</hi> still be our <hi>own.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But if a <hi>Third</hi> herein must take a <hi>Part,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Let it the <hi>Love</hi> be, that's in <hi>either Heart.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>IRIS,</hi> her Answer to <hi>TIMANDER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Fifth Letter.</head>
            <p>I Was much surpriz'd yesterday, when I read the Verses, you made upon my Blushing, after you had promis'd me solemnly, you wou'd make none. I cannot tell, how to forgive you: But, if you think to qualifie the business, by saying, That Love seated himself on my Cheeks, being unable to enter into my Heart, you are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179501:28"/>wonderfully mistaken. An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Crum, this, of Consolation for me! he might have been in my Heart; I shou'd not have been offended at it: At least, he would not have appeared there. But, publickly, before all the World, to climb up on my Face, this way (let me tell you) was somewhat too Triumphant, and by no means agrees with my Constitution. Yet after all, what ever dexterity he pretends to, he has taken his measures very unwisely: For, to enter into a place, where he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get free and ready Admission, he should not come into the Visage, bare fac'd and disclosed: He ought to travel in by-roads; and, this he may be assured from me, that, when he shall appear thus, I will defend the passage. Now, do I imagine you, Friend, in the horrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est desperation, that is possible! nevertheless, recollect your self,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:179501:28"/>for I am not so naughty as you wou'd guess me to be from my Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side: And, to speak the truth, a tepid Passion would suit very well with me. I would with all my heart know the nature of it: but I cannot as yet see into the thing. To be plain with you, Master, you teach me nothing at all: I accosted you, yesterday, with so still and un-interrupted an Air, that, for my particular, I cou'd not keep from being somewhat vex'd at it: 'Tis your fault, and none of mine: And I hope, that to be reveng'd on the Verses, you compos'd on my blush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you will permit me to Bomb you with some few Rhymes.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:179501:29"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Irregular</hi> Verses against <hi>TI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANDER.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>I've <hi>try'd</hi> it, but I cannot <hi>find</hi> This <hi>trouble</hi> of the <hi>Heart,</hi> they say's so <hi>sweet:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Still all its <hi>Motions</hi> kindly <hi>meet,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Still the same <hi>unfixt thoughts</hi> are in my mind.</l>
                        <l>I've <hi>try'd,</hi> but if I can't this <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> get,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Scholar</hi>'s Duty's <hi>done;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The <hi>Master</hi> all the <hi>blame</hi> doth fall <hi>upon,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>If her <hi>Heart</hi> has been <hi>taught</hi> no <hi>more</hi> as yet.</l>
                        <l>Of a <hi>fit Age</hi> I am to <hi>Learn:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Adapted</hi> is my <hi>Blossom</hi> to your <hi>turn:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And you may <hi>thank</hi> your <hi>self,</hi> if I</l>
                        <l>Still <hi>sundging</hi> in my <hi>quiet Ignorance</hi> lye.</l>
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:179501:29"/>
                        <l>But why such <hi>ill words</hi> of <hi>indifference?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>If any <hi>indifference</hi> be in my <hi>Breast,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>You should leave <hi>all</hi> to <hi>Time,</hi> or do your <hi>best,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>T' <hi>expell</hi> it thence.</l>
                        <l>Indeed, <hi>that thing,</hi> which you call <hi>Tenderness,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Well, have you <hi>Painted</hi> out to me;</l>
                        <l>And, this <hi>Idea</hi> in its <hi>flourishing</hi> dress</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Heart,</hi> as <hi>blind</hi> as 'tis, doth <hi>love</hi> to <hi>see.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Yet hath it <hi>still</hi> this great <hi>unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To <hi>see,</hi> it is not <hi>blest</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>With the <hi>Substantial</hi> and the <hi>Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi> Guest.</l>
                        <l>Bring <hi>this</hi> to <hi>me,</hi> and also <hi>bring</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Me</hi> into its <hi>Acquaintance,</hi> that I may</l>
                        <l>No longer in <hi>unlearned</hi> quiet <hi>stay,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But <hi>restless</hi> Love may bear me on the <hi>Wing.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>'Tis no <hi>great business,</hi> which I <hi>ask,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Tho this <hi>disorder great</hi> I'd have to be;</l>
                        <l>I'd have all <hi>nature</hi> quite <hi>subdu'd</hi> in me:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Acquit</hi> your self, then, of the <hi>task:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:179501:30"/>
                        <l>And, since my Heart <hi>offers</hi> so wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly,</l>
                        <l>You shall <hi>instruct</hi> it, or shall <hi>tell</hi> it, <hi>why.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This challenge is very Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: It is, as if I should cast my Heart at your Head. But in fine, I am somewhat Vain glorious, and, when I undertake a Thing, I love to go through with it, immediately. If, on such an occasion, this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardness be dis-allowable, it does not belong to you now to consider Formalities so Critically: For (not to be tedious) I see you already disposed to try once more in my favour the Path of Tenderness; and it wou'd be rediculous to see a Man alone in it, where People generally go two and two toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: So that I shall presently expect your Instructions, not only for your own Glory but (perhaps) for your Interest also.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:179501:30"/>You have already judg'd, <hi>Madam,</hi> the thoughts of this Letter to be so New and so Singular, that I shall add no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing further concerning them. I have left the Verses, as they were written with her own hand, chusing rather to see them in their Native and Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal simplicity, than to give a supersluous Polishing and Adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them, which would perhaps spoil, or at least might alter their Natural estate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in consists all their Beauty. But, this was the Rejoinder, which a day or two afterwards I return'd to her Letter.</q>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="letter">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:179501:31"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi> to the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Siuth Letter.</head>
            <p>I Very heartily pardon the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, you have written against me: That fine and polite Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poon ought rather to attract my Praises than my Resentment. I confess it, I was exceedingly in the wrong to make Love ascend up into your Face; whereby he appeared with too great a Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour: And, as you say well, he ought to have taken more by ways.</p>
            <lg n="1">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:179501:31"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'm</hi> our, <hi>my beauteous</hi> Iris, <hi>cruelly</hi> out: Better <hi>I might have</hi> plac'd <hi>this</hi> Love,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And through</hi> subtle <hi>by ways</hi> brought it about,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Till</hi> fixt <hi>at your own</hi> Heart <hi>it</hi> ceas'd <hi>to</hi> move.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not on the</hi> glorious <hi>Cheek it should sit still,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But little</hi> cunning <hi>Journeys go:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Obscurity <hi>with its own</hi> mind <hi>suits</hi> ill,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And</hi> unreserved <hi>splendour is its</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test <hi>foe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>I will undertake, you think, you have not so much Reason, as you really have. Most admirable is the desire which you signifie, to be instructed in Passion: 'Tis
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:179501:32"/>good, to satisfie a Curiosity, which ought to be natural to you: But lay it not to my charge, if when you saw me, you felt not the same trouble, I felt at your approach. If you had given me your Heart, as I had given you mine, you wou'd have been sensible of the same Emetion with me: And, if you had left it but one moment to my disposal, I engage, it shou'd have receiv'd a great deal of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in following my Lessons. Give me leave then, Lady, to try my Poetick faculty in a Repartee to your Verses.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> quick experience <hi>on</hi> you <hi>to</hi> bestow</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of the Heart's</hi> charming <hi>trouble,</hi> gentle <hi>woe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which you feel</hi> unknown, <hi>while you</hi> wisht <hi>for't so;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Indulge <hi>some</hi> moments <hi>to</hi> Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<hi>'s Song:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor</hi> that, <hi>nor your</hi> experience <hi>shall be</hi> long.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="1">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:179501:32"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>This</hi> sweet disorder <hi>straight shall</hi> spring,</l>
               <l>Without <hi>your</hi> knowledge <hi>of the</hi> thing;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Straight shall you</hi> plainly <hi>see,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> means <hi>all</hi> honestly:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Never was</hi> Scholar <hi>more by</hi> Master <hi>lov'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor than an</hi> Iris <hi>apter</hi> Scholar <hi>prov'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis very</hi> true, <hi>you'r</hi> all <hi>o'er</hi> fair,</l>
               <l>Fair <hi>as bright</hi> simpering Roses <hi>are;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But still with</hi> them <hi>you</hi> miss</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your own</hi> affecting bliss,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And still with them,</hi> unhappy, <hi>don't</hi> receive</l>
               <l>Ought <hi>of the</hi> blest Impressions, <hi>which you</hi> give.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>But if</hi> indifference <hi>is to</hi> thee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such</hi> dull <hi>uneasie</hi> Company,</l>
               <l>Make <hi>an</hi> exchange <hi>of</hi> Hearts,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or else into</hi> two Parts</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cut</hi> mine, <hi>and take it's</hi> Tenderness <hi>to</hi> you:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Soon will</hi> both halves <hi>be</hi> one whole <hi>in us</hi> Two.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:179501:33"/>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>If you'd be</hi> Ignorant <hi>no more,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Enough <hi>I'll give of</hi> Learning<hi>'s store,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So you your</hi> Heart <hi>do</hi> give,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And then you shall</hi> perceive;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That I'm no</hi> Novice <hi>in this</hi> brave employ,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And since it</hi> offers fair, <hi>I'll teach you,</hi> why.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>This defiance is very singular on my side: You have lash'd out so far as to say, that you do as good as cast your Heart at my Head; but, I will never believe it, till I get it betwixt my Fingers. However, you are in the Right, when you say, you find me inclin'd once more to shew you the Path of Tenderness. Nevertheless, take this from me, I am not cut out of an humor to march alone there any long while: It is an High-way which is horrid troublesom, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in solitude and no Company is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly very dreadful and dangerous,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:179501:33"/>I cannot promise you, according to the frame, I find my Heart in, but it may be robb'd and stripp'd by some thievish Eyes or other: But, if yours do but once keep it faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Company, it defies all the Eyes in the World to do it any harm, or so much as to bid it, Stand.</p>
            <q>I was a good while, <hi>Madam,</hi> without seeing her, after I had got this Letter to be put into her hands. An old Uncle of hers, that was a very devout and very morose Abbot, gave her not all the Liberty she cou'd wish. I was oftentimes stark mad at the peevishness of this old Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and a super-annuated Aunt, who confining her to her way of living, cou'd by no means agree with our Genious and Disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. However Patience we must have: But a violent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietness began to let me know,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:179501:34"/>that this same Correspondence, which at first only appeared to me as a play-thing, was become a real concern of Heart, on my side. That captivated Liberty, I had to see and discourse her, augmented the desire: That de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire was succeeded by a sharp and goring inquietude, and that inquietude presag'd, what was about to befall me. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this, as the minds of Lovers are very uncertain, I had a large interval of ease; I was no more troubled with those impetuous Motions; I return'd again to my first opinion, that it was all toy and foolery: And, being quite wearied out with not meeting that lovely Person, even in those places, whither our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion does regularly call us, I writ to her this Letter.</q>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="letter">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:179501:34"/>
            <head>To the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Seventh Letter.</head>
            <p>YOU have not answered my last: I cannot set my Eyes upon you, neither are you a whit eager to give me an occasion. I am persuaded, that to avoid the meeting Men, you neglect the Divine service: This does not shew much Devotion. A Man can spy you no more at Church, than if you were either <hi>Calvinist</hi> or <hi>Lutheran:</hi> This is an horrid Scandal. Heretofore, I have seen you very attentive at Sermon. I am affraid, this hardness of Heart reaches as far as your Soul it self: To be so indifferent to all manner of Things, is a very wicked dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position with reference to good Thoughts: And it is too much
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:179501:35"/>at one time, to mind neither God nor Man. I fancy my self to day in a very prone and opposite humor to Preach to you a while upon a good many Articles, since you never look after the Sermons of our Pulpiteers: And, as indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is your Original sin, you are to endeavour the destroying it Root and Branch in your Soul: But, I believe, I shall but lose my time and pains, to make you believe any thing. You are a Profligate Creature [that's certain] having neither Faith nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, in point of Love: And, notwithstanding all the Zeal, wherewith I am animated, your Heart has</p>
            <l>Got such an <hi>unbelieving</hi> trick,</l>
            <l>That 'tis in <hi>Love</hi> an <hi>Heretick.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Let <hi>Homilists</hi> say what they <hi>will,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>It is so <hi>hard,</hi> so <hi>rocky</hi> still,</l>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:179501:35"/>
            <l>That no <hi>Impressions</hi> can be writ</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Faith</hi>'s Characters in it.</l>
            <p>For all this, I will send you <hi>the Love,</hi> that hath mollified my Soul, and drawn me out of the errors wherein I lay, to Preach to you and direct your judgment for some time. He will endoctrinate you so tenderly, that I am sure, you will say, he is an able and a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Preacher: For there is no Heart so obdurate but he can break: And without question, he will bring you to Repentance and a good Mind, if you give him but the least Overture into your Heart. You will find, that he is eloquent, that he most vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorously persuades what ever he insinuates, that his thoughts are bold and noble, his Expressions clean and just, and that he infuses into the Souls of his Congregation, a certain sweetness, that draws
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:179501:36"/>and charms them how and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he pleases, and that convicts Hearts, the most hardned in the error of indifference. Be you one of his hearers, fair Heretick! de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the way of Perdition, and enter into the right Path, wherein predestinated Souls do walk! That is the surest and most pleasant Road, where Love conducts you. <hi>Fiat.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>IRIS,</hi> her Answer to <hi>TIMANDER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Eighth Letter.</head>
            <p>UPON my Word, a pleasant device: This, and Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem of your Love! Hey day, that he may pay me a Visit, to take upon him the Habit of a Preacher!
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:179501:36"/>Who could ever know him under this disguise? Is it the business of Love to meddle with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Manners? I am sure, he would say very irregular things on such an encounter: For, it is none of his Talent, to reason well. I doubt, he did not reflect suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently on the qualifications, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite to such a <hi>Person,</hi> and he took this Part at random and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerately: But who looks for any Prudence and Discretion in him? And besides, this is not the thing I complain of. Was there any necessity of using a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zening trick with an Heart, that had dealt so fairly upon the Square with you? This I wou'd willingly upbraid him himself withal: But, seeing I was never yet in his Company, and you are extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly familiar with him, I desire the kindness of you to deliver the Letter (here enclos'd and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrib'd)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:179501:37"/>your self into his own Hands.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>The Epistle of <hi>IRIS</hi> to Love.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tho I have not the</hi> Honour <hi>to know</hi> you,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet</hi> (pardon <hi>my</hi> Presumption) <hi>to</hi> write <hi>now</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'm</hi> fixt, <hi>Dear</hi> Love: <hi>For, as you may</hi> remember,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You on the</hi> Ninth-day <hi>of (I</hi> think) Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember;</l>
               <l>[Sorry <hi>I am, if I</hi> mistake <hi>a</hi> time,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So</hi> Solemn, <hi>yet I not</hi> mistake <hi>i th'</hi> Rhyme]</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> choose <hi>a</hi> Master <hi>for me</hi> you <hi>took</hi> care,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who no</hi> extraordinary <hi>pains doth</hi> spare,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> make <hi>me</hi> Love <hi>him, and so</hi> acts <hi>his part,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That I must</hi> thank <hi>you now with all my</hi> Heart.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Therefore, sweet</hi> Sir, <hi>I'll</hi> deal <hi>wi' you like a</hi> Friend:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For, if your</hi> knowledge <hi>does to me</hi> extend,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis but as yet an</hi> Half-acquaintance, <hi>though</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It may to' a</hi> greater Stature <hi>one day</hi> grow.</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:179501:37"/>
               <l/>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Mean time, I'll tell you</hi> this <hi>between us</hi> two;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In the</hi> wide world <hi>there's</hi> one, <hi>that has of</hi> you</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> good opinion; <hi>yet the</hi> Party <hi>once</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Could not</hi> your Name <hi>without a</hi> blush <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now, if this</hi> scraul <hi>should</hi> happen <hi>to take</hi> Air,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What</hi> lifted Hands, <hi>what</hi> Clamours <hi>would be</hi> there?</l>
               <l>With you, <hi>they say,</hi> all Correspondence is</l>
               <l>Death and the Devil of all unhappiness;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>How</hi> ill <hi>this</hi> sounds? <hi>I've</hi> always <hi>had, 'tis true,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A most</hi> particular <hi>esteem for</hi> you:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ile ne'r</hi> deny<hi>'t: And 'tis my</hi> present <hi>sense,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Young</hi> Verdant Hearts <hi>may with</hi> some <hi>Love</hi> dispence.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You,</hi> Squire, <hi>no doubt, as</hi> knowing, <hi>that an Heart</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Finding the</hi> Menace <hi>of your</hi> fatal Dart,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Takes up</hi> defensive <hi>Arms, and</hi> braves <hi>the</hi> Foe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With me most</hi> wisely <hi>have not</hi> acted <hi>so,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But</hi> advanc'd <hi>slyly up,</hi> incognito.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But,</hi> Sir Love, <hi>hark you,</hi> one word <hi>in your</hi> Ear!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> take <hi>on</hi> you <hi>the</hi> rueful <hi>Character</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:179501:38"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Gospeller, <hi>you</hi> chuse <hi>wrong</hi> foolish Measures:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In bearing</hi> Baxter <hi>there are no</hi> strange Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not</hi> you <hi>can</hi> fright <hi>one half so</hi> much, <hi>I vow,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As such</hi> starch'd Gentlemen <hi>of</hi> awful <hi>brow.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tell me some fine</hi> sweet things, <hi>and I shall</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">Cleaveland:</note> wear</l>
               <l>Such precious Words, like Jewels, in my Ear:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For I like the least</hi> Complement <hi>much</hi> better,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thau the</hi> best Sermon <hi>upon Love's</hi> Dead Letter.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No more</hi> such Fetches: <hi>Try a</hi> nearer <hi>way,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And to my</hi> Heart, <hi>like</hi> Love, <hi>thy</hi> self <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Age <hi>is not so</hi> terrible: <hi>At least</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your</hi> own <hi>shape will take</hi> more <hi>than</hi> that <hi>of</hi> Priest.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My</hi> Heart <hi>is full as</hi> young: <hi>Yet</hi> (don't mistake)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It will</hi> not <hi>for a</hi> fluttering Cupid <hi>quake.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis all</hi> alone, <hi>and</hi> knows <hi>not what to</hi> do:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pray</hi> come, <hi>and</hi> play <hi>with it</hi> together <hi>now.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From such a</hi> Guest <hi>a</hi> Visit <hi>will be</hi> kind,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And you shall very</hi> good Reception <hi>find:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Till then I bid,</hi> Adieu, <hi>in sort most</hi> Fervent;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And, for</hi> Form<hi>'s sake, I rest</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="letter">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:179501:38"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi>'s Answer to the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Ninth Letter.</head>
            <p>WITH your last Letter I am not altogether so well satisfi'd: It is too full of Wit and Gayety, and I cou'd not find one grain of Passion in it. To what end, all that fine Railery upon Love, turn'd Preacher? However, this I will say for him, he was gallant enough (if you remember) and had nothing of the Air of an austere Pedagogue. If I had lov'd you less, I should have excellent Thoughts of <hi>Iris</hi> her Epistle to Love, it being writ in a natural and Epistolizing Style, very much resembling <hi>Horace</hi>'s way, tho I presume, you never read him: But, upon the main, I begin to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:179501:39"/>perceive, that so much Wit does but fret and vex a Man, when the Heart is not concern'd in the affair. Our Love Advertisements, indeed, drew their first Original from a perfect Frolick: But I am now sensible, what ever resistance I made, my Heart is become a Party, and if yours does not second it, it must needs pass its days very unpleasantly. Or else, if I had the same Power over mine, a s you have over yours; if I cou'd be as undisturb'd as you, there wou'd be some equality in the Case; or, if you had the same Emotions with me, things would hang better balanc'd, and in a clearer state of Reason. The trouble and disorder I fell into yesterday, when I saw you, had fifty times more Eloquution, than a thousand of your Letters, let 'em be never so Witty.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:179501:39"/>
            <l>In this <hi>Attack</hi> of <hi>mind</hi> so <hi>plainly</hi> seen,</l>
            <l>Why cann't the <hi>Tongue</hi> now speak the <hi>sighs</hi> within?</l>
            <l>The <hi>Trance,</hi> Oh, is too <hi>much</hi> to <hi>tell:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Raging Joy</hi> is, all, <hi>unspeakable.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>I am sorry, these four Verses have escap'd my Pen: For, in sum, I am an arrant Fool for writing to you in a soft and passionate strain, when I ought to trifle as you do, and to keep at a good distance from all Engagements. I throughly understand, what you aim at: And doubtless, you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve with all your Wit about you, that the Passion, I begin to have for you, shou'd degenerate into a bare esteem: Yes, to punish you for your indifference and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-handdealing, it is your desert, that I had as much Wit as you: And in good time (by the blessing of Heaven) I may have some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to me. In the mean while,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:179501:40"/>forbear Wit, I beseech you of all Loves: And let us have some more Passion. I know, how yours explicates it self: But, let me hear the Language of your Heart!</p>
            <l>Alase! hath <hi>your</hi> Heart <hi>nought</hi> to say,</l>
            <l>Your Heart, which makes me thus <hi>complain,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And while <hi>my</hi> Heart sighs <hi>Night</hi> and <hi>Day,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Cannot <hi>yours</hi> learn to <hi>sigh</hi> again?</l>
            <p>I know, what a Latitudinarian it is: It sticks to no Principles: It defends it self by evading shifts and general delusions. Some time or other, I design to write so fierce and keen a Satyr against Wit, that you shall regret your having so much: But as I have not the leisure at present to compleat such a Work, I here in the interim send you a <hi>Rondelay,</hi> differently modell'd from the way of the Antients, and gifted with the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:179501:40"/>fresh and reviving Air of this Age, to answer that which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hears'd to me last, whose Word was <hi>No:</hi> Wherein you declar'd, that you will neither surrender your Self, nor so much as hear the Lessons of your Master.</p>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> hate <hi>you,</hi> Yes, <hi>I do</hi> Protest, <hi>I</hi> hate:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Heart <hi>is a meer</hi> Gull <hi>and</hi> Cheat,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which</hi> understands <hi>the Art of</hi> self-defence,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And I shall</hi> never <hi>get the</hi> Prize,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>While it still</hi> No's, <hi>and still</hi> denies:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You</hi> shuffle <hi>with me,</hi> Dear Impertinence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>But bring this</hi> Jargon <hi>to true Reason's</hi> Test:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Soften the</hi> Hardness <hi>on't</hi> at least.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And when the</hi> faithful <hi>Swain</hi> Timander <hi>says,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tell me, <hi>young Iris,</hi> is your Heart</l>
               <l>Tender, soft in every Part?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In the</hi> same Tone <hi>let</hi> Iris <hi>answer,</hi> Yes.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:179501:41"/>
            <p>Pray, make good use of this Lesson, and make no more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers to your Master in such cold Terms.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Answer</hi> to the former Verses.</p>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>Yes, <hi>I hate</hi> you, <hi>I swear, I</hi> hate:</l>
               <l>Nothing <hi>so</hi> sure <hi>on</hi> this <hi>side</hi> Fate.</l>
               <l>Words, <hi>which, I</hi> take <hi>it, will</hi> surprize</l>
               <l>You <hi>and your</hi> Love, <hi>tho</hi> both <hi>so</hi> wise.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Words, which I</hi> borrow'd <hi>from</hi> your Pen,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And now</hi> return <hi>'em</hi> back <hi>again:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> cursed thought <hi>for our</hi> Love-Elegies!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such an</hi> Avowal <hi>speaks not th'</hi> Heart</l>
               <l>Tender, soft, <hi>in every</hi> Part:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In th'</hi> Art <hi>of</hi> Love <hi>you are to</hi> learn,</l>
               <l>[<hi>You that pretend,</hi> Sir, <hi>to</hi> discern</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So</hi> much <hi>in</hi> it] <hi>that we are</hi> never</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> understand <hi>ought in our</hi> favour,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or</hi> Writ <hi>or</hi> spoken, <hi>when in Love we</hi> burn.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:179501:41"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>Nothing, <hi>but from my</hi> Cruelty,</l>
               <l>Timander <hi>is to</hi> hear <hi>or</hi> see.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But</hi> now — <hi>I</hi> think, <hi>and think</hi> aright,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And</hi> spy <hi>the</hi> true <hi>from the</hi> false Light,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This same,</hi> I hate you, <hi>is in</hi> Rhyme,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> pretty <hi>turn or</hi> goodly <hi>Chime;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And should not make</hi> you <hi>the</hi> same <hi>Words to</hi> Write.</l>
            </lg>
            <q>This, <hi>Madam,</hi> was then the State of our Amorous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, which was in a good measure well establish'd: But my distress was, that I could see her but very rarely: Yet when ever I could snatch such desireable and expected Minutes, I was wrapt into such Joys, as I want Words to express them. Every day I found some new Charms in her Wit or in her Person: And just at that nick of time, when I began to be
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:179501:42"/>influenc'd by their Power with a great deal of pleasure, I was forc'd to leave that Country. An indispensable affair call'd me to P—at a Season, when I hop'd to tame and cicurate her young Heart with Love. Upon the necessity of this departure, so black a Melancholy seiz'd me, that I could not but own, my Heart did terrible Violence to it self by a remote Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Object of its Love: But there was no help for it. In all places, I sought <hi>Iris</hi> out, to bid her <hi>Adieu,</hi> and to beg her Letters to me during my Voyage, but all to no purpose: For, I cou'd not meet with her at home. I visited many of her Friends, but could not hear of her: And, whatever Address and application I us'd to meet with her, it prov'd vain and fruitless: So that I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:179501:42"/>to depart without bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her, <hi>Farewell.</hi> I mounted therefore my Horse, very gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and over-whelm'd with such dark thoughts, as her indifferent Heart did in no wise deserve. In the mean time, I made a pleasure of this Gloominess, because 'tis ever a sweet thing to Love: It was now no less than Three years, that my Heart had been almost buried in a monstrous inactivity. I was glad to find my self again in a Road, where a Man may take much delight to Ramble, Wherefore, I abandon'd it to its good or ill Fortune. A Man is sufficiently rewarded for his Passion by the Passion it self: And notwithstanding the odd displeasures, it may bring from the Indifference or Rigour of a Fair Lady, yet it never fails to have some very pleasing and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:179501:43"/>sensible Moments: And I am of opinion, that laying all things together, the perplexities of Love are almost as much to be valued, as the Pleasures we enjoy else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. I went my way there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, fill'd with these Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Speculations: Or, rather (without acting the Hero of a Romance) filled with the charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Idea I carried along with me, I arriv'd at <hi>Paris</hi> more in Love than ever I was with ..... I knew not, what Course or Bias to take, to write to that amiable Person, that had the intire Possession of me. But at length, I writ to one of her She friends, and I enclos'd a Note in the Letter, which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired her personally to deliver safe to <hi>Iris.</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="letter">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:179501:43"/>
            <head>To the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Tenth Letter.</head>
            <p>SINCE <hi>Madamoiselle de</hi> ....... has had the goodness, to take on her the Charge of this Letter, I have ventured to write to you at this time. I know, indeed, I ought not to do it in the least; and I ought to dream as little of you, as you have thought of me, now an whole Month together. I look'd up and down for you with such an earnestness, as, all the World will grant, your Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inclinations did not deserve; and I was not able to bid you, <hi>Adieu,</hi> tho my Passion, at least, might have Compounded for such a thing, before my departure. I know not, whether you know it, or whether you took the trouble to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:179501:44"/>give your self Information thereof. But, the Town I left without a sight of you: Yet nevertheless, I do but see you too well here every day. How? cannot thirty Leagues distance you from an Heart, which you care for so little? And cannot this Heart, so indifferent to you, be ever di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided from you?</p>
            <l>Tho you <hi>slight</hi> it, tho it <hi>has</hi>
            </l>
            <l>On its <hi>own side,</hi> against <hi>you,</hi> local <hi>space;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>No where,</hi> but it doth your <hi>bright Image</hi> see,</l>
            <l>As if <hi>Love's God</hi> gave you <hi>ubiquity.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>You have render'd it insensible to all the Pleasures, that here present themselves in Crowds and Rendezvouzes, so that it may only have a sensation of its own Misfortunes: This is it's sole Employment. Yet still—if you wou'd give some mitigation to 'em by a Letter: But-hold, do not
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:179501:44"/>write to me, a Correspondence is very dangerous with you. I have already learnt so throughly well, after what manner you write, and your Letters wou'd compleat my Ruine, if I could read over an hundred and an hundred times the Character of an Hand, that has so much Wit at its Fingers ends. In the mean while, I am Lodged at ..... And let what will come, this is my direction. I will not tell you by an Historical Retail all my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions, since my departure. Why shou'd your Idea thus fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me incessantly? And is not <hi>Paris</hi> a Sanctuary against this beautiful Image, that hobgoblins me continually? I will say no more to you now; I fear, I have said too much already. I expect an Answer to this, with an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, which I wish you cou'd conceive. Dream sometimes of a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:179501:45"/>Man, that is employ'd only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, and will be so all his Life-time. <hi>Adieu.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>IRIS,</hi> her Answer to <hi>TIMANDER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Eleventh Letter.</head>
            <p>I Was strangely surpriz'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Letter from you by <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> ...... The course was a very Indirect one, but I forgive you for this time: For I have some Rigours to bestow upon you some other ways. I say, Rigours; see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I fancy my self in a sufficient Condition, to use this Term of speech. Undoubtedly, you have some Passion for me: But you have stay'd somewhat too long to explain your self. The time
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:179501:45"/>is over now, that I shou'd make any return or acknowledgment: It will be unseasonable, since all further Communication is abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to be broken. I can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern no occasion to continue it: And besides, it wou'd be an ill Management of a body's time, to enter into an affair, during a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. Absence is the Rock of every Passion, and thereon we shall presently see yours split it self. It is much better, to return you your Heart in an handsom way, than to expect, till you take it away from me. This is ever to have a Right over you, to be capable of such an Estate, as to restore you to your pristine Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. For this reason, if the business depends upon me, you are free; Or, if your Heart has constantly made its abode about and near mine (as you wou'd sain perswade me) it may depart, when it pleases.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:179501:46"/>
            <l>I, let <hi>your</hi> Heart of <hi>mine</hi> now <hi>take</hi> its <hi>leave,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yet its <hi>obligements mine</hi> will ne'er <hi>disown:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>No <hi>time</hi> shall <hi>it</hi> of <hi>Gratitude bereave,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nor shall your <hi>cares</hi> on it away be <hi>thrown.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>It may, <hi>perhaps,</hi> in <hi>time</hi> its <hi>Master</hi> pay:</l>
            <l>So, let him <hi>quit</hi> it till the <hi>Payment day.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>But, to return back to my Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, from which I have insen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly swerved; if it be true, that my Idea torments you so much, and even <hi>possesses</hi> you in the worst sense of the Word, I here send you a Receipt to exorcise it out. Do put repeat over five or six times all the hard Words in this Letter: And they will be a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Preservative against all the most charming Ideas in the World. <hi>Adieu:</hi> Have as much care of my Tranquillity, when the occasion shall offer it self, as I have now of yours: And above all, write no more to me; for I can no longer receive any Letters from you,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:179501:46"/>without running the greatest of dangers; seeing I am beset by spyes on every side.</p>
            <q>This Letter I had hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, but a most urgent hurly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burly of distraction laid hold of my Soul. Her threatning she would write no more to me, gave me true alarms: And to speak the truth, without scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulously consulting, if my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs required my longer stay at ...... where I then was, I came away the day following with such an unaccustom'd plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, as is felt by none but those that are mightily in Love, and have an ardent desire to see a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain its Object. I reached ..... and the next day after, I obtain'd this Letter to be given her.</q>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="letter">
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:179501:47"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi> to <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Twelfth Letter.</head>
            <p>AS soon as I had read your Letter, I departed at the same instant from ...... to bring you the Answer my self. I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got all my affairs, to mind those only of my Heart, the greatest I ever had in all my Life. I could not sustain without dread that cruel Menace, you made me, of breaking our Commerce. Ah! Lovely ..... have you duly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on the Weight of those terrible Words? Was it not enough, not to see you, but you must de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive me of the happiness of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to you? I see through your Intentions: You have, perhaps, a desire to disintricate your self
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:179501:47"/>from a Man, whose Passion is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesom to you. You will soon at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your end: Not to see you, and not to write to you any more, are two such things, as will quickly reduce me to a Condition of never troubling you further. Hereby, you will have shattered my Chains to pieces in an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som way. You will do your self the kindness, without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Speak the word, and I return to ..... fall back, fall edge: Repose your self upon my Anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and they will afford you Contentment. But still, this is an ill employment of a Man's time to enter into an affair during a Separation. Absence is the Rock of all Passions, and you will see mine (like all other Lovers) split upon that Rock in a small time. Cruel Creature! How many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious words and opprobrious terms hath my Heart (if I might
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:179501:48"/>dare to say it) uttered against you, who do not deserve them? You are vety ill acquainted with its Passion and your own Power over it, to believe, that absence can change and ever alter the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it has of you. But what am I doing? No, no, you do not deserve, that I shou'd disabuse you: Break my Chains, if you can, and return me that Heart again, and that Liberty, which you make so little account of, since you cast them at my Head with so much indifferency.</p>
            <l>Am I in <hi>fit Condition,</hi> to <hi>receive</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> you <hi>give?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>If they have <hi>cost</hi> you <hi>nothing</hi> to <hi>retain,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Why do you <hi>send</hi> them <hi>back</hi> again?</l>
            <p>You fear, that absence may destroy a Passion as strong and forcible as mine. I would pardon you this fear, if you really and sincerely had it. In the mean
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:179501:48"/>time, ever since I knew you, have you not been evermore absent in relation to me, and have I ever lov'd you the less for't? I see you so seldom, that it wou'd be the same thing to be an hundred Leagues from you, if I did not hope sometimes to meet with you. But still, I find you but too often out, to my discomfort: However, I would fain come to such a pass as to obey you, and resume that Heart, which you send me back again. But to answer you in your own Rhymes:</p>
            <l>Of <hi>yours,</hi> alass! can <hi>my Heart</hi> take its <hi>leave?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>No! it's <hi>obligements</hi> it will ever <hi>own:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>No <hi>time</hi> shall <hi>it</hi> of <hi>slavery bereave;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>If it's <hi>cares</hi> on <hi>yours</hi> away be not <hi>thrown.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That <hi>time,</hi> when <hi>Iris</hi> can her Master <hi>pay,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Dun</hi> will <hi>surely</hi> come on <hi>Payment-day.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:179501:49"/>
            <p>How have your Verses redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled my Passion? With what a tender and sprightly Air are they inspir'd, that allures and puts me into despair at the same time? For, it may be, you wou'd not be very sorry to lose a Master, that will never leave you nor forsake you, but will patiently wait for the Retributions you owe to the Care, which his Heart takes in instructing such an ignorant Heart as yours, and that makes so little use of his Lessons. What you add after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, is well-natur'd and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching: <hi>Take as much care of my Tranquillity, as I at present take of yours,</hi> &amp;c. What a fatal Care do you take of mine? Alas! If I took the like inspection over your Repose, I doubt, you would have very little of it. How rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less and melancholy would you be; and, in few words, how ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly would you love me? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:179501:49"/>now see, what you wou'd have me do: I am return'd from ..... only to see and write to you: I have, without any hesitation, quitted all the Pleasures of the Court, to come and make mine to you. Behold, what I do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being belov'd; and judge of what I should do, if I were some degrees less unhappy.</p>
            <q>After she had receiv'd this Letter, I continued a long time without any answer to it; and, not meeting the young <hi>Iris,</hi> whom I was inflam'd with a desire to see, in my impatience I writ the following Letter to her.</q>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="letter">
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:179501:50"/>
            <head>To the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Thirteenth Letter.</head>
            <p>SINCE the writing of my last, I have sought for you, but was always frustrated. Are you invisible to me? Or, what have I done, that should deprive me of the pleasure to see you, tho I am come thirty Leagues expresly for that purpose? I perceive, you care not much, whether I be here, or in any other place: I see, it is all one to <hi>Iris,</hi> and she finds no interest nor importance in the matter.</p>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>Mounted <hi>upon the</hi> Wings <hi>of</hi> Love,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From</hi> far <hi>to</hi> thee <hi>I swiftly</hi> Rove:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> rage <hi>to</hi> see</l>
               <l>That <hi>which my</hi> Heart <hi>so much</hi> adores,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And would make</hi> Gods <hi>turn</hi> Bigot-worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:179501:50"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Eight <hi>days now are</hi> past <hi>and</hi> done,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Since I these</hi> Racks <hi>have</hi> undergone:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In</hi> every <hi>place</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> seek <hi>you, yet</hi> no where <hi>can</hi> find,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But</hi> only <hi>in the</hi> Torments <hi>of my</hi> mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet</hi> one <hi>Beam,</hi> fairest, <hi>of your</hi> Eye,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Would</hi> make <hi>all these</hi> black <hi>Terrors</hi> fly:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or could I</hi> send</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> sigh, <hi>would you return a</hi> Line?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But</hi> nought <hi>from your</hi> Old-rigor <hi>you'l</hi> deline.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas! why</hi> can't <hi>I my Old heart</hi> regain,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which</hi> you <hi>in such</hi> hard pleasing <hi>chains</hi> detain?</l>
            </lg>
            <p>In good earnest, if I had been somewhat wiser, I shou'd have obey'd you punctually: I shou'd have re-call'd my Heart to <hi>Paris,</hi> that doubtless would have diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me extremely: But all the Company, I had, was only your
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:179501:51"/>Letters and my own Melancholy. I return'd thence inconsiderately at a time, when a thousand plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures would have laid hands upon me in a place, where they all meet as in a Centre. But what? Was I capable of taking them, when I was so far distant from you? I know not, whether you keep accounts of all that I do for you: But I may say of your Heart with regard to mine:</p>
            <l>
               <hi>Never</hi> was Heart <hi>behind-hand</hi> more,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Never</hi> did <hi>run</hi> so <hi>much</hi> o'th' <hi>score.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>It is my <hi>judgment,</hi> I <hi>declare,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>It <hi>ought</hi> to <hi>own</hi> its <hi>master</hi>'s eare.</l>
            <l>To <hi>think,</hi> that he should <hi>teach,</hi> is <hi>rude,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For <hi>nothing</hi> but <hi>Ingratitude.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As he's a <hi>gen'rous honest</hi> fellow</l>
            <l>(At <hi>least,</hi> as he is <hi>pleas'd</hi> to <hi>tell</hi> you)</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Deal</hi> by him <hi>fairly:</hi> And since you may</l>
            <l>
               <hi>All</hi> with one <hi>upright sigh</hi> re-pay,</l>
            <l>Besides th' <hi>acquittance,</hi> I'll maintain,</l>
            <l>He'll give the <hi>money</hi> back <hi>again.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:179501:51"/>
            <p>You see, how reasonable, and how easily satisfi'd your Master is:</p>
            <l>A <hi>small</hi> Proposal, <hi>Iris,</hi> this!</l>
            <l>One <hi>sigh</hi> is no such <hi>mighty thing:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And yet to <hi>thank</hi> you he'll not <hi>miss,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But for <hi>one,</hi> in his <hi>turn,</hi> will <hi>thousands bring.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>You see, you will lose no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by the bargain. In good truth, my Adorable ...... I am here to deal with you very plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and from the bottom of my Heart. Nothing is comparable to the passion and esteem I have for you, but that to speak all in a word, it is proportion'd to your Merit: But I did not believe, that what I thought only to be meer Fooling and Metaphor, would ever come to turmoil my Heart at this rate, and make so weak an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression upon yours. Your back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardness
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:179501:52"/>to let me know, that my Passion is not altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to you, doth torment me, and perhaps may in time destroy it. Let me explicitely know, what Pulses your Heart beats up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Point: I have a mind to understand my good or my evil destiny; and I should think my self the most happy of Men, if your indifference or coldness crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the same Sentiments in my Soul: And hereby, you will red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>integrate that Liberty, which you so calmly send me back. But, tell me, <hi>Iris:</hi>
            </p>
            <l>When you my <hi>Liberty</hi> restor'd,</l>
            <l>With so much <hi>unconcern</hi> and <hi>Cruelty;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Did not your <hi>Heart</hi> the <hi>fatal</hi> words <hi>deny,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To <hi>lose</hi> a <hi>man</hi> of <hi>such fidelity?</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Send me an answer to this, or rather, I humbly supplicate you, disengage me quite, or else rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage me for ever.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="letter">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:179501:52"/>
            <head>
               <hi>IRIS</hi> to <hi>TIMAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Fourteenth Letter.</head>
            <p>THAT, according to my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention you have quitted indifference, I find, <hi>Timander:</hi> And because this is a thing of some consequence and moment to me, I owe it at least some reflection. I begin to take Cognizance, that you are more deeply dipt, than it is necessary for my quiet. I see with some Grief, that one shall not preserve you long; unless one run the same danger with you. So that a body ought to consult her self about it: And this affair, between us two, deserves highly some considerative thoughts.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:179501:53"/>
            <l>
               <hi>Good now!</hi> What <hi>troubles</hi> tour this <hi>Heart,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When it is <hi>forc'd</hi> two <hi>distinct</hi> ways to <hi>part?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When I see <hi>you,</hi> my <hi>Glory</hi> draws</l>
            <l>Me to <hi>engage</hi> you <hi>further</hi> in the <hi>Cause:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But, on <hi>my</hi> side, my <hi>youngish Breast,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Which finds it self with <hi>horrid</hi> dangers <hi>prest,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Dares not <hi>leap</hi> into Love's <hi>Abysse,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But a <hi>free Dispensation</hi> would <hi>possess.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Reduc'd, thus, to the <hi>cruel</hi> choice,</l>
            <l>To <hi>risque</hi> mine <hi>Heart</hi> or else my <hi>Shepherd lose,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thus by a <hi>sad Dilemma</hi> bound,</l>
            <l>What <hi>course</hi> for <hi>wise Election</hi> can be found?</l>
            <p>How luscious wou'd it be to be belov'd, if alternatively, one did not expose one's self to Love! What pleasure is there in viewing with a disinterress'd Eye a Lover, while he heaves up serious and unhypocritical sighs? Why should a body fear to have the same Lot one's self another day? But why do you exact it already from me? It is indeed, one of the greatest
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:179501:53"/>pieces of Honesty, I ever heard of, that of yours, to ask one sigh, and then give a thousand for it: Yet, alas!</p>
            <l>'Tis the <hi>first sigh,</hi> which the <hi>whole</hi> Heart does <hi>win:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And when it's <hi>once</hi> betray'd into the <hi>gin,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>hottest</hi> heaving <hi>sighs</hi> are all <hi>allow'd:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Who</hi> will give <hi>one,</hi> will <hi>forthwith</hi> give a <hi>crowd.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>In effect, this is the first Hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, that is pay'd to Love: The rest of course follows after, and every thing in the sequel appears easie. It is the first entrance of Love into the Heart; whence depends all the devastation and havock, that is made there: And it is this entrance, which we ought to dispute with him Inch by Inch. So that I must vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly keep upon my Guard: But already</p>
            <lg n="1">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:179501:54"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>Dare you <hi>Securities</hi> require?</l>
               <l>Just has your <hi>Heart</hi> now <hi>foster'd</hi> the <hi>desire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>trembling</hi> Flames scarce <hi>rise</hi> from the <hi>new Fire.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Is this a <hi>time</hi> to <hi>fear?</hi> is this</l>
               <l>Your <hi>wishing, sighing dying</hi> tenderness?</l>
               <l>Rather the <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>both</hi> our <hi>Liberties.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>Oh! for an <hi>Heart</hi> always to <hi>fear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It plainly <hi>shews</hi> th' <hi>inherent weakness</hi> there;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heav'n</hi> keep me from <hi>'t!</hi> all <hi>Cowardize</hi> I <hi>forswear.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>To speak unfeignedly, I wou'd avoid as much as possibly the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you; since the fear of Loving
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:179501:54"/>destroys the Calmness of ones hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor: I look upon it to be worse than the evil it self. But when all is done, I fansie, a body is troubled enough to find a Lover the Mistris of ones Heart: Yet then, the thing is past and over, and I believe, one tasts some Repose, when there remains nothing to be managed. But to how many unmerciful alarms does a young Heart expose it self, that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us'd to 'em? What a world of tears, perils, and uneasiness must it pass through the first time it suffers it self to be attac'kd? Why should I expose mine to all these Troubles without any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity? That wou'd be meer fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: No, it shall engage in nothing: Rather resume your indifference, that will be a good Caution for mine, which I ought not to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to save your Passion in its Birth. Now, how rational is this?
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:179501:55"/>Yet nevertheless, I cannot resolve designedly to destroy a Conquest, which has already cost me some trouble to make.</p>
            <l>
               <hi>Yes,</hi> tho my <hi>Reason</hi> doth my <hi>Love</hi> oppose,</l>
            <l>Yet I <hi>confess</hi> in the <hi>dispute,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>By'ts <hi>bold,</hi> tho <hi>weak</hi> resistance in the <hi>close,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Reason</hi> is not so <hi>Absolute.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Continue</hi> in my <hi>Chains</hi> then <hi>Captive</hi> still:</l>
            <l>I have <hi>decreed;</hi> let happen <hi>good</hi> or <hi>ill.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>This passage is somewhat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate as to the acceptation, and I will not swear, I take it in the Literal signification of the Words. In the mean time, when you think fitting, you may rerurn to ..... I will find out some shifts to continue our Correspondence: But pray, observe all along the faults I commit, either in the Verse or Prose, and mark 'em down for me; so that at least my mind may get some improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the hazards, whereinto
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:179501:55"/>I run my Heart. <hi>Adieu.</hi> To be sure, admit no Confidents: Two Witnesses are sufficient for one Heart: If the other Heart will be medling, let it alone, it will do no mischief: But a Third Person wou'd be not only incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient but troublesom.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi>'s Answer to the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Fifteenth Letter.</head>
            <p>HOW enchanting is your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Divine ....... I have been just now a solemnizing the Reading of it with a thousand sighs: And the answer, which my own honor commands me to make, wou'd be to make none at all. If I let you see in my
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:179501:56"/>Letter the weakness of my Wit, you will at least discover the strength of my Heart's sentiments: And if you have the advantage over me to write a thousand times better than I, I shall have at least that of Loving a thousand times better than you, which you dare not bring into Contestation with me. But, to give a regular and methodical Reply to your Letter, you are too rational to believe me to be too much engag'd: If I am really so, it's rather for your Interest than my own; and if I wou'd have you run the same Perils with me, it is to let you tast the same Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures. So to answer your Verses with the same Changes.</p>
            <l>About a <hi>Shepherd</hi> is your <hi>Heart</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Perplex'd,</hi> and <hi>knows</hi> not to take <hi>either Part?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As soon as it <hi>another</hi> draws,</l>
            <l>It ought to'engage <hi>it self</hi> in the <hi>same</hi> Cause:</l>
            <l>They <hi>both</hi> should the <hi>same dangers</hi> press,</l>
            <l>Which is the <hi>self-same pleasures</hi> to possess.</l>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:179501:56"/>
            <l>See at your <hi>Feet</hi> the Shepherd <hi>bound,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Kissing</hi> with <hi>Reverence</hi> the <hi>Holy ground,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Oh! <hi>raise</hi> him up by a <hi>free choice,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And, <hi>save</hi> the <hi>Shepherd</hi> and your <hi>doubtings lose.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Wherefore, know, fair <hi>Iris,</hi> that it is a sad, a very sad thing to be belov'd, if we do not Love, that which loves us.</p>
            <l>
               <hi>Reciprocally</hi> Love should <hi>move;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For <hi>Love</hi> was <hi>only</hi> made for <hi>Love.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>single</hi> Hearts the <hi>flame</hi> is <hi>slight,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>two,</hi> magnificently <hi>bright:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>one,</hi> Love is but <hi>Partial,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>two</hi> united, <hi>one</hi> and <hi>all:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>two</hi> it <hi>clubs</hi> the <hi>sacred</hi> Treasures</l>
            <l>Of <hi>pleasing</hi> Torments, <hi>torturing</hi> pleasures:</l>
            <l>The <hi>she</hi> for <hi>him</hi> was <hi>made</hi> no <hi>less,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Than th' <hi>Lover</hi> for the <hi>Loveress.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Why, then, shou'd you be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of having the same Fate with me? What wou'd you do with my Passion, if it was not followed by
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:179501:57"/>your own? Believe me, without this it wou'd prove a thing whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly useless, and perchance very cumbersom. Do not stand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Guard, therefore, if I desire a sigh of your Heart, for that by advance and Anticipation mine has already pay'd it with a Million of sighs.</p>
            <l>'Tis this <hi>first sigh,</hi> which my <hi>Heart</hi> doth <hi>deserve,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>If <hi>you</hi> would from your <hi>Skepticism</hi> swerve:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pardon</hi> me, <hi>Nymph,</hi> if <hi>Trembling.</hi> I <hi>surmize,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>You have <hi>already</hi> known a thousand <hi>sighs.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Indeed, according to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, wherein you reason, and draw deductions and Corollaries touching Love tenderness, I am terribly affraid, lest your Heart has already felt its Assaults from some other Enemy, and has had some other Master, whose Lessons may have preceded mine.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:179501:57"/>
            <l>For <hi>my</hi> part, in this <hi>state,</hi> 'tis my <hi>sole task,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Iris</hi> one <hi>civil Question</hi> new to <hi>ask:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Was it <hi>true Love,</hi> or purely <hi>nature</hi> brought</l>
            <l>You so much <hi>knowledge,</hi> and <hi>experienc'd</hi> thought?</l>
            <p>'Tis true, if your knowledge intimidates me, yet nevertheless your Youth and small experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence reassures me, on the other hand.</p>
            <l>For, who could <hi>thoughts</hi> of <hi>fifteen</hi> summers <hi>link</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With so much <hi>justness,</hi> and <hi>nice care?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Who could e'er yet <hi>depaint</hi> down, what they <hi>think,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With so <hi>Polite</hi> and <hi>Curious</hi> an <hi>Air?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>thought</hi> and <hi>Style,</hi> both <hi>Symmetry</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Shine</hi> in her <hi>Paper,</hi> as her <hi>Face.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>For my share, I have not black Eye enough, to dive into this Miracle, which I admire, but dare not plumb to the bottom. I fear
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:179501:58"/>every thing, but have not Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to hope for any thing. All that I can say to you, amounts to this: That, an Heart (me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks) ought once to be ill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, to defend it self so well afterwards. Pardon this jealous Nicety (young <hi>Iris</hi>) I beg it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my knees at this distance: Alas! I wish your Heart knew the price of that first sigh, which mine requires of it.</p>
            <l>When we do such <hi>Securities</hi> require</l>
            <l>Against an <hi>Heart,</hi> that sets us all on <hi>fire,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>We <hi>ought</hi> to <hi>know</hi> the <hi>Tenderness,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And <hi>price</hi> of all our <hi>Liberties:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>This is my <hi>fear,</hi> but Pardon, <hi>Iris,</hi> this,</l>
            <l>Which <hi>springs</hi> from <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>tender jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Fear, therefore, no more to fear me: I am not so dangerous to your Tranquillity, as you have been to mine. But take fresh Courage, seeing I have not your
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:179501:58"/>merit. And, I fear very much to my disquiet, that I shall find you too calm and unconcern'd.</p>
            <l>So, let <hi>your</hi> self be <hi>kindled</hi> by <hi>my</hi> Love,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>And you will have</hi> no reason <hi>to</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>And,</hi> when <hi>you can but</hi> once <hi>your</hi> fires <hi>approve,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Then will you <hi>cease</hi> to <hi>fear</hi> me <hi>once</hi> again.</l>
            <p>Nevertheless, if it be true, that to make a Conquest of me has cost you some trouble, it shall be well repay'd. This passage in your Letter is so delicate, that I have read it over a thousand times, as well as the Verses that follow, which I dare not touch, for fear I spoil the admirable sense of them. The only fault, I find in your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is that reflection in the Prose, which comes after those lovely Verses. And, since you command me to tell you your faults, that your Wit may reap some profit
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:179501:59"/>from the dangers, wherein you engage your Heart (which is a divine thing) you may be pleas'd to rase these Words out of your Letter. <hi>This occurence is somewhat delicate as to the acceptation; and I will not swear, I take it all Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</hi> Oh, harsh and salvage Prose, after such kind and tender Verses! As for the rest, we will have no Confidents. I will give you my Love-letters my self, and will only trust my own individual self with the sentiments of my own Heart: Give me yours, in like manner, at our next meeting. But, most especially, let two Hearts as well as a couple of Heads enter into this Negotiation, so that things may stand in a just Equality.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="letter">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:179501:59"/>
            <head>
               <hi>IRIS,</hi> her Answer to <hi>TIMANDER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Sixteenth Letter.</head>
            <p>IN short, you take it ill, that I appear so knowing in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Passion. The truth is, I was surpriz'd my self as well as you, to find so much Illumination in me, that I had never look'd for. I should, no doubt, have ask'd my Reason, whether it was that, which had taught me so much: Perhaps it would have been in a strange taking, to have made an answer. Such sort of Questions do ordinarily terrifie it, and put it to confusion and slight; but that your Fears and Jealousies are able to fetch it back again, tho it had strayed very far. What Injustice do you commit against a
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:179501:60"/>young Heart to believe, that it hath felt the power of Love, when I confess to you from the bottom of my Soul, that it avoids it as the most dangerous thing in the World?</p>
            <l>If this <hi>Sigh-commerce,</hi> which two Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers-<hi>use,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To Lovers <hi>pierc'd</hi> by the <hi>same Darts,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Makes <hi>the Felicity of</hi> Hearts,</l>
            <l>Why <hi>should I all</hi> those Pleasures <hi>still</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse?</l>
            <p>Truly, you have not considered your assertion throughly enough. If to sigh in Concert and together, be so pleasurable a thing, how can you think I would avoid it, when I have had experience thereof, and would preserve my own Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, by the knowledge I have of the pleasure one takes in losing it? Make all these things hang together, if you can. However, we are to believe, that there is
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:179501:60"/>much pleasure in preserving a body's Liberty, seeing you say, I know the price of it so well. After all these words so plain and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, any other besides my self would think Love's party to be the weaker: But, I expect, 'till you pronounce hereon out of your Professorian Chair.</p>
            <l>And, if this <hi>Heart</hi> should form a <hi>vow,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Which <hi>hangs</hi> now in <hi>suspence,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>I'm sore <hi>afraid,</hi> that it would <hi>bow</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>favour</hi> of <hi>indifference.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>I here send you my Epistle to Love, revis'd, corrected, and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented: (The Second Edition:) Pray write me your thoughts of it.</p>
            <q>You admire, <hi>Madam,</hi> at the manner wherein this Letter is turn'd and winded, and how full of Reasoning it is. For my
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:179501:61"/>share, I never saw so much fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and subtilty: And, you see that an Heart, defended by so great a Wit, must needs be of difficult access. However, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> the greatest difficulties do only irritate our Passion. I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, I must e'en march step by step; and this would prove an affair of a longer breath and continuance, than I imagined. This Letter was only full of Wit, but the former had some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more Tenderness: So that my Heart floated betwixt hope and fear. I very seldom saw the young <hi>Iris,</hi> and I could only write to her: And still, frequently, I was a long time without giving her my Letters, it being a Month and longer, before I could find her. She very seldom came into Publick, and the over-strickt Regularity of her Benefic'd Uncle would
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:179501:61"/>hardly let her go to Mass; not considering, that such strain'd Punctilioes of exactness do sometimes provoke young People, to take, of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, those Liberties, deny'd them by others. But, though this transcendent Creature had very little Liberty, she never took any of her self, but liv'd under a Monastical constraint, that extremely vex'd and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted me. Wherefore, I was a long while without meeting her: But, at length, as I pass'd one day in the street I met her, and after a light Conversation, I had only time to give her this Letter.</q>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="letter">
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:179501:62"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi> to the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Seventeenth Letter.</head>
            <p>IN good earnest, I am but sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily edifi'd with your back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardness to let me have an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of meeting you. But what do you think upon? You have very fairly made me spoil in my Pocket those answers, I was to give you: And, you will not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to confide 'em with such People, as might do us great and good service in an harmless Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence, which you need not take so much pains to conceal from the World, seeing your Heart hath kept at a distance from all Ingagements in it, and mine is the only one that is interressed; and your Uncle, as devout as he
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:179501:62"/>is, can find no fault with it. A Man with a Sword by his side makes him as red as a Turky<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock; and unless a Man wear a little Collar like him, and a little Periwig, he cannot come within fifty steps of your house. For my particular, I am almost re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd to make such a Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phosis of my self to pay you a Visit in a Fools Habit, and to take on me the Air of a <hi>Tartuff</hi> to accommodate my self to his sight. But however, ought not you, for all him, to facilitate the ways to me of seeing and speaking with you? I must confess, your Wit has amaz'd me, I was bewil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to find so much Flame and delicacy in it; I never expected to meet in the barbarous Country a Spirit, that had so small a tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture thereof, that made so easie a passage into the manners and customs of the World without any
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:179501:63"/>practice, and to which meer na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Parts supply'd the place of all the most consummated Art and Experience. I deal with you here with the greatest sincerity, and from the very bottom of my Soul: I have conceiv'd so high an esteem of you, and I am so fully satisfi'd of your worth, that it lies upon you, to take some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more notice of this estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which you hold so indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and which will carry me much further than it self. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless, if I should make this my Period, it wou'd be well enough: But, I am sensible, by what it has cost me already, what it will one day cost me. I have taken much delight in writing to you, and receiving your Letters, that have enchanted me: And I am persuaded, That <hi>France</hi> will some time or other own it's great Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to me, for having help'd
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:179501:63"/>to cultivate one of the most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Genii</hi> it ever produc'd. You have made me prolong soundly and abundantly that short abode, I was us'd to make in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. I parted thence contrary to my custom, with such an horrid darkness upon my thoughts, as I never had since my acquaintance with you: And I return'd hither with such a desire, as I am unable to represent. Here I continue still upon your sole account and consideration: Whil'st it is well known, that 'tis now above Eight years, that the Month of <hi>October</hi> has not seen me at ..... I could wish, it were possible for me to establish a Commerce, that begins to become very dear and near to me. I cannot consider without the greatest Terrours imaginable, that I must leave you suddenly. I am almost distracted with endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to find out ways of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:179501:64"/>to you, during a long ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence. I know not, whether you wou'd consent to it: Scarce have I seen you for these two Months, that I know of: And yet I find, I am as far advanc'd in my Passion, as if I had never seen you. But, why should my concerns tear me from you? And yet, why should I be so sensible of a departure, which you look upon with so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardless an Eye? I have hardly taught you any thing in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Tenderness; and yet, you have inspir'd but too much into me, to the destruction of my Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity: So that I may disconso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lately say, that the Master has taught the Scholar nothing, and the Scholar has learnt the Master too much. You are very desirous, I should engage my self; but you will not hearken to your own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement. Now, is this reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or fair? You would have me
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:179501:64"/>alone bear the whole burden of Passion during a tedious separation, yet will not participate of it with me your self.</p>
            <l>Speak, <hi>Fairest,</hi> and your <hi>Mind</hi> explain,</l>
            <l>Though I shall <hi>hear</hi> it with <hi>much pain:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For, I'm <hi>resolv'd</hi> before we <hi>part,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To <hi>listen,</hi> if <hi>each other</hi>'s Heart</l>
            <l>Be well <hi>cemented</hi> in <hi>Concert:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>This is a <hi>shrew'd step:</hi> And howe'er I <hi>meant</hi> it,</l>
            <l>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>haps <hi>you</hi>'l give me <hi>Reasons</hi> to <hi>repeat</hi> it.</l>
            <p>It's the same thing to me: I wou'd fain learn your Resolutions hereon, and what Progress my Love has hitherto made in your Heart.</p>
            <l>Alas! What strange <hi>Auxieties,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Do <hi>my</hi> Heart <hi>seize,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When <hi>yours</hi> I see</l>
            <l>To <hi>mine</hi> so <hi>careless</hi> to <hi>reply?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Give</hi> me some <hi>hearty</hi> [tho't be <hi>little</hi>] Food:</l>
            <l>I <hi>cannot live</hi> on bare <hi>Ingratitude.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:179501:65"/>
            <p>Upon my Soul, very often I know not, what is become of me. You have made me change altogether my manner of life. I was natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of a very free and unconfin'd Temper: But now, I have neither that Pleasantness nor Liberty of mind, which was accustom'd at other times so faithfully to keep me Company. All my business is about you: I fly the World, which I once passionately lov'd: I have found my self drench'd, for this good while, into a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found dotage, whereof you are the greatest cause; and I am not as yet awak'd out of it but by the trouble I have to leave you. I am come into a desperate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: And this departure strikes as much at my Heart, as if I was tenderly belov'd by you. I beseech you to involve yours a little more than you do, in an affair, wherein mine so strongly interesses it self:
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:179501:65"/>But you mind nothing of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; you will not share with me the pleasure I have to see you; and you rob me of those Moments, that are so dear to me, and which you make to pass away with an inconceiveable swiftness. If I hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to meet you, and am a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with you, you are presently for going away with an uneasiness, that extremely torments me: You are always pretending some fear to be any long time far from home. How much more piercing Anguishes than these would I expose my self to, provided I cou'd have the pleasure to enjoy so sweet a Moment: But, upon that upshot, take this into your Consideration, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so agreeable in human Life as a reciprocal Passion; and make this your scope to aim at:</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:179501:66"/>
            <l>That we our <hi>Radiant Hearts</hi> employ,</l>
            <l>In <hi>one</hi> united <hi>Beam</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>shine:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>So that the <hi>doubt</hi> shall be, <hi>if mine</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Or <hi>yours</hi> the <hi>greatest</hi> pleasures do <hi>enjoy.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>A positive and Categorical An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, I conjure you. <hi>Adieu.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>IRIS,</hi> her Answer to <hi>TIMANDER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Eighteenth Letter.</head>
            <p>I Did not believe before now, upon my Reputation, <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> I was so much indebted to you. I did not reckon your return from ..... in the number of my debts: And, if I was bound to place it to the foot of the account, I shou'd find my self unable to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit or discharge it: My whole stock of acknowledgment wou'd
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:179501:66"/>not suffice, and it looks like too hard measure to drain it quite dry. Do not go to persuade me, that you did it for my sake: You are out in your reckoning there, and I will tell you how: I ever fram'd to my self a very pleasant Idea of Love: I fancy'd it only proper to amuse and divert an Heart, and I did not believe it capable of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording more serious Employments. But, in short, if your Love makes you to return thirty Leagues ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly for the sake of an ill-esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish'd Correspondence, I am of opinion, it may carry you much farther: Insomuch that, hereupon I ought to stand upon my Guard, having no desire nor ambition to go so swift a pace. Lord bless me! to ride full thirty Leagues (and I shall never forget it) for the sole interest of your Passion! This af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frights me most horribly. In God's Name, let us have only (if it be
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:179501:67"/>possible) a tenderness in Picture; and let our Heart have no sense of what our Hand shall dash and blot upon Paper; seeing this same dangerous Passion leads People so swiftly and such a great way. Besides, do not complain, that I stay so little while with you, when I meet you. You ought rather to judge, I have such. Reasons that perplex me, it may be, as much as you, which are the cause of those sudden Retreats, that are some of your grievances. <hi>Adieu.</hi> Above all, let us have a Passion, that will not plunge us too deep, and from which we may disengage our selves when we think fitting, in regard it is so dangerous to feel one that hurries People so far, from whence it is a great piece of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to return.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="letter">
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:179501:67"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi>'s Answer to the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Nineteenth Letter.</head>
            <p>IF you had seen the melancholy, into which your last Letter put me, you wou'd, questionless, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, you had ever writ it. I know not whether I shall have strength to make a Replication: I see so much Ingratitude and so much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference in't, that it ought to recall mine. But how! after three Months fixation to the most pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionate tenderness, is this all the Progress I have made in your Heart? You treat and regale me with an affection in Picture. Yet, what glimmering of hope from all this? You even doubt, whether I turn'd expresly from ..... to see you. What signifies it, if I make
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:179501:68"/>that of my Heart my chief and primary Concern, when it is only an amazement to yours (as I have already told you) and if I lose my own Repose, when yours continues intire still, and unsha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? I'll vow, you are very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just to upbraid me, that my Passion carries me too far, in making me come thirty Leagues. What way hath it made you go, whereof you have reason to complain? You ought not to be extraordinarily fatigu'd with so long a Journey, since it never brought you but from ..... whither you have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the pains to come sometimes; and you have render'd me thirty Steps for those thirty Leagues. You have mighty great occasion (I warrant you) to make some ease after such a toilsom expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Indeed, <hi>Madamoiselle,</hi> I am not yet acquainted with you: I forgive you that Picture affection,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:179501:68"/>with which you affront a true tenderness; since that you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand not the force of those cruel words. No, most undoubtedly, with all your Wit you do it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the force and extent of those fatal and dead doing Words; for as much as your Heart should first be as tender as mine, to feel all the bitterness of them. Oh, that I should ever know you! By what contrivance of Fate did I first see you? And, what Devil put me into the hands of such a young gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and shifting Wag, that knows not yet all the evil she does, and all the good she may do? Why am I persuaded of your Value and Excellence, in loving you so ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly? Why cannot I resume my Heart again, and blot and dash it with indifference, by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrance to your <hi>Lely</hi>-affection? I would give my self certain strokes and airs of confidence and high-spiritedness;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:179501:69"/>which, yet wou'd melt to nothing when I come near you. But stay! should I burn in good earnest, shou'd I have a true inquietude, and (in fine) a true and a rich Passion for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Person? I believe, in good faith, nothing of all this. In the mean time, let me know the last resolve of your Heart, whether it will engage with mine, or disen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage it altogether. I shall go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in these two days: I expect its answer with impatience, which will bring my destiny. There is not one moment to be lost; since on this moment depends the loss or the liberty of an Heart, which hath been but too much <hi>Yours.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="letter">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:179501:69"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi> to <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Twentieth Letter.</head>
            <p>THE day before yesterday. I waited for you at the place, whither you promis'd me to come, but to no purpose: There, you made me stay full four hours, till half an hour after seven. The expectation of you did horribly turmoil me, and this perplex'd me as much as the Letter, I receiv'd from you. I took the History of <hi>France,</hi> I read something in it; I discours'd at random; I sigh'd, and, in fine, I appear'd, in such a dumpish hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, that some of the Company could not forbear taking me up for it. The Persons, with whom
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:179501:70"/>I was, tho very lovely, could bring no Consolation for your absence. You have given me so great a disgust for all the rest of the World, that I am become insupportable to my self. Yet however, I am not satisfi'd, why I lay so great stress upon an interview, which you have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd me. After the Letters, you have written to me, I ought to quit you absolutely: But, alas! meeting you yesterday, I saw something so tender, so soft and sweet in your Eyes, which made reparation for the cruelty of your Letters, that I could not keep from falling once more into the snare. You promis'd me to be at ....... and my Heart promis'd you (in spight of my teeth) to love you more than ever. But, why do you break your Word? Where was you? What was you doing? What was you busie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout?
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:179501:70"/>In what Company did you cozen the time, that was due to the Eve of my departure? Oh, that a little effective and real Passion would inspirit me instead of that Picture-affection, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with your two last are topping full! 'Tis true, your Air is kind and tender enough, so that a Man does not know what to think of it. Take, now the same Air in you Letters: You ought to modifie and sweeten the fire and lustre of your Wit with a mixture of Passion; and, in brief, trifle a little more seriously. Leave the motions of your mind to be Conducted by your Heart: But, especially teach me, before my departure, in what situation I am with you: Perhaps, I stand at a great Elongation. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, let what will happen, speak out, tell me boldly, <hi>I hate you,</hi> if you dare not tell me <hi>I Love you:</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:179501:71"/>Peradventure, the first will be less fatal than the second, which will cost me, without doubt, the Repose of my whole Life. An answer with the soonest.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>IRIS</hi> to <hi>TIMAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The One and Twentieth Letter.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>FArewell,</hi> Timander, <hi>O farewell, nor</hi> stay</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> hear <hi>the</hi> Words, <hi>which you</hi> desire:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For, how</hi> can <hi>I, at th'</hi> warning <hi>of</hi> one <hi>day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> kind return <hi>make to your</hi> fire?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or, if I</hi> could, <hi>tho after</hi> bloudy <hi>strife,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I could</hi> not <hi>speak the</hi> Sentence <hi>for my</hi> life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:179501:71"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>But, still</hi> alas! — <hi>Whence comes this</hi> ugly sigh?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What</hi> secret Fiend <hi>does</hi> hag <hi>my</hi> Breast?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> fear, <hi>I</hi> give <hi>my self a</hi> cursed lye:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh, no!</hi> Love's <hi>Empire I</hi> detest.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Without</hi> true Protestant reserve, <hi>yet</hi> Zeal,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I say,</hi> Farewell, <hi>Timander, O</hi> Farewell!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>If</hi> my Eyes [foolish things!] <hi>do you</hi> inform</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of any</hi> Love, <hi>or</hi> God <hi>knows</hi> what,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My</hi> Mouth <hi>can</hi> soon, <hi>can in a</hi> thundering storm</l>
               <l>Tell <hi>you quite</hi> other News <hi>than</hi> that:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But,</hi> see, <hi>without</hi> Confession <hi>on</hi> my <hi>part,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If you can</hi> Love <hi>me with a</hi> stedfast <hi>heart.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>One</hi> single <hi>Heart,</hi> you say, <hi>cannot</hi> suffice:</l>
               <l>Two <hi>Months</hi> vain <hi>Transports</hi> drain <hi>a Lover;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But, how shall I</hi> know, <hi>if from</hi> Love <hi>they</hi> rise?</l>
               <l>Time <hi>may a</hi> diff'rent <hi>Cause</hi> discover.</l>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:179501:72"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>With what</hi> Front <hi>can</hi> you, Men, <hi>pretend to</hi> Name</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So</hi> soon <hi>a</hi> true <hi>and</hi> intermutual <hi>Flame.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Your <hi>Heart</hi> long <hi>time in</hi> Prison <hi>cannot</hi> dwell:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Chain <hi>it slips, and slips the</hi> place;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But,</hi> mine <hi>when</hi> fixt, <hi>as in</hi> Monastick <hi>Cell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cannot get</hi> free <hi>from the</hi> Embrace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You,</hi> Men, <hi>do</hi> Love, <hi>like</hi> Modish Cloaths, <hi>put on:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We</hi> think<hi>'t an</hi> Habit <hi>of</hi> Religion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>But,</hi> this <hi>along with you,</hi> Timander, <hi>take:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Love, <hi>that doth</hi> all <hi>things</hi> over-come,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Me</hi> one <hi>day</hi> one <hi>of his</hi> sad slaves <hi>may make,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tho by a</hi> slow, <hi>yet certain doom.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But,</hi> here <hi>in</hi> solomn <hi>wise,</hi> this Oath <hi>I'll seal:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whatever</hi> amorous <hi>Martyrdom I</hi> feel,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> never <hi>will one</hi> word <hi>of it</hi> reveal.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>These are my Thoughts, <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> upon the Declaration, which
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:179501:72"/>you exact from me. Therefore, desire such a thing no more: It is of most necessary Consequence, that your Heart shou'd take its leave of this affair, as soon as mine shall be in an estate to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it. I would fly you, if I had not the Right and Prerogative to banish you: Or I would banish you from my presence, if I had the Power to do so. What a wretched success is this of so brave a Passion, and what will be fav'd from the Shipwreck and Ruins of our interchangeable affection? You would admire me, and I should complain of you; this wou'd be all the fruit of that so soft and tender Love. Believe me, we may admire our selves afresh, both the one and the other. You may wonder at a young Heart, that knows already most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently well, how to defend it self, as if it had been attack'd all its
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:179501:73"/>life long, that is acquainted rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily with all the cunning sleights of Love, and can avoid 'em with dexterity and ease. But do you likewise manage the business so, that I may stand astonish'd at the Constancy of your Heart, to sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount and vanquish all the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of mine. 'Tis not improbable, but it will retain it not long, and it will entertain some Passion both for its own and for your Repose, seeing the Accounts are little dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent between a beloved and a loving Heart. Wherefore, never despair to see it one day in the same case with yours; But, by the force of Cares and of Affection, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry out the obdurateness you shall find there: Long-suffering and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severance prevail over the most Opinionative and Rebellious dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions. Do not then, fear the effect of all my Menaces; and without having recourse to an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowal,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:179501:73"/>wherein my Glory and Honour may be somewhat inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ress'd, there are a thousand ways of discovering a New born Passion, which a body sees to grow up with pleasure. If the Tongue dare speak nothing, at least the Eyes have an Eloquution on such an occasion: And, a little disorder and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity explain it with more deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, than a Confession, which would make one blush:</p>
            <l>And, <hi>above</hi> all, a certain <hi>Languishing,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>[The <hi>Hool,</hi> that <hi>construes</hi> well the <hi>mind</hi>]</l>
            <l>Will very <hi>soon</hi> tell you the <hi>thing,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Whatever</hi> morose <hi>Rigour</hi> now you <hi>find.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="letter">
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:179501:74"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi>'s Answer to the young <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Two and Twentieth Letter.</head>
            <p>YOUR Copy of Verses wou'd have infinitely aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the esteem, I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cev'd of your Genii, but that I have been otherwise, too well convinc'd of its Perfections; and if I had as free and as disengag'd a Wit as you have, I should im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately set upon an Answer: But the motions of my Heart do quench and offuscate the clearness of my Soul, and I have but just Light enough to see, that I have none at all in an approximation to you. All that I am able to rejoyn, comes to this, that I love you
<note n="*" place="margin">éperduëment, perditè.</note> des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately. Behold all
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:179501:74"/>my Verses, all my Wit, all my Merit! I am not in a condition to add any thing more: My Love, my Departure, my Anxietude do take me up so entirely, that I have hardly the leisure to breath.</p>
            <l>
               <hi>Judge,</hi> Lovely <hi>Iris,</hi> of my <hi>doleful</hi> state:</l>
            <l>Scarce <hi>equal</hi> is my <hi>whole Heart</hi> to my <hi>sighs:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>How</hi> then can I <hi>Love-jingles</hi> ruminate?</l>
            <l>I <hi>Love,</hi> I <hi>go,</hi> and you <hi>this</hi> Love <hi>despise.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>What dainty fine Verses should I Compose, if I had that Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, which you enjoy? But, in few words, take some of my Passion, and give me some of your Wit: Of them we may make a more comfortable Tempa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature. You will receive much more pleasure, than you have, and I shall have less Pensiveness: And, upon the main, I should write to you more curious Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:179501:75"/>and you would have more passionate Sentiments. However, you, you have nothing but Wit, and to my Lot falls nothing but Affection.</p>
            <l>
               <hi>Cruel</hi> Division for a <hi>Lover</hi>'s Heart,</l>
            <l>Where no <hi>one</hi> else will <hi>take</hi> a <hi>part!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>A <hi>Barbarous</hi> Providence, where <hi>you</hi> possess</l>
            <l>The <hi>Wit intire,</hi> I <hi>intire Tenderness!</hi>
            </l>
            <p>In the mean time, I assure you, that you will have a thousand pleasures, you never had, if you were further drench'd in this affair: Some Passion would make you slip over a thousand yawnings, since without Love pleasures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves are faint and insipid.</p>
            <l>Yes, <hi>you</hi> ought to <hi>envy</hi> Love:</l>
            <l>It's <hi>delicious</hi> Languors can,</l>
            <l>When <hi>they</hi> the <hi>Heart</hi> do <hi>briskly</hi> move,</l>
            <l>Only <hi>make</hi> the <hi>joy</hi> of <hi>Man.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:179501:75"/>
            <p>I have a thousand prety thoughts to tell you upon this Topick, but that I want time, and my Stars will not let my concerns be in so good an humor, as that I should be able to write fine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and conceits to you. I love you, I am departing; I shall see you no more: I know not how I stand with your Heart; I am sure, mine is wholly taken up with yours. What Fears, what Anguishes do rack my Soul! I shall not see you of a long time; I shall not have the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent delight to hope for such a thing: I shall be more than fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days in expectation of so heavenly a moment. I shall no more feel that emparadis'd emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which your approach strikes me withal! That so sweet, so sensible a confusion, when you give me your Letters with your own hand, and receive my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:179501:76"/>from mine before Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that know nothing at all of the matter, and from whom we conceal our Intrigues! Above all, remember the trouble I was in yesterday, when I gave you my Letter, and receiv'd yours. This will spare me the pains to make some Verses in return to those admirable ones of yours. Your Prose is very chast and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate; and if I had time to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer it, I would tell you in two words, That, if you once lov'd me, you would be so far from flying or banishing me, that you wou'd seek me out every where as diligently, as I inquire after you. Let us not cast away our selves in the Haven, but happily Land on the fortunate Shore; So that our Vicarious Passion may not be split or broken to pieces, but may receive a much stronger and more lasting bond of Concord
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:179501:76"/>than ever: And what will be the issue of all this, but that which I told you last?</p>
            <l>A <hi>thousand</hi> and a <hi>thousand</hi> Wishes,</l>
            <l>A <hi>thousand</hi> and a <hi>thousand</hi> Kisses,</l>
            <l>A <hi>thousand</hi> and a <hi>thousand</hi> Pleasures</l>
            <l>Will <hi>follow</hi> in <hi>eternal Treasures.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>I cannot see, how such a Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wreck can be so very, very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. More particularly, think, that you lose a great deal of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure by defending your self so long. Your Heart is an excellent spot of Ground to be made Arable; but suffer no new Thorns to spring up in't. Admire, therefore, my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate Fidelity, but do not tire it out by so long a resistance. And especially,</p>
            <l>
               <hi>Hasten</hi> that certain <hi>Languishing</hi>
            </l>
            <l>(The <hi>Hool,</hi> that <hi>constuers</hi> well the <hi>mind:</hi>)</l>
            <l>Be <hi>sure</hi> it <hi>quickly</hi> tell the <hi>thing;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And let that <hi>morose</hi> Rigour <hi>once</hi> be <hi>kind.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="letter">
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:179501:77"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TIMANDER</hi> to <hi>IRIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Three and Twentieth Letter.</head>
            <p>I Did not much wonder to be forgotten by <hi>Madam</hi> ..... But I was in good hopes you wou'd remember the promise you made me, to send every <hi>Wednesday</hi> to the Post-house for the Letters, I shou'd direct to you under the Name of <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> D ...... I have writ two, that have lain there a long time, and which I have sent .... to fetch back, for fear they should be lost. I am much troubled at the forgetfulness of the beautiful D .... who had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to write to me. Do not repine, I befeech you, if I have quitted you for her, seeing she hath as much Merit as your self.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:179501:77"/>Her last Copy of Verses was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>supportibly killing: Her wit, her delicacy, and the justness of her Expressions have been admired here; and Persons of the highest Quality have been extremely ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest to be acquainted with her charming Person, as they already have knowledge of the beauty of her Wit: Insomuch as</p>
            <l>Her <hi>Verse</hi> and <hi>Prose</hi> they thought so <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That, to <hi>compleat</hi> my utmost <hi>Punishment,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>They seem'd to <hi>long</hi> for this <hi>forbidden Tree,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Whose <hi>early Fruit</hi> had <hi>op'd</hi> their <hi>Eyes</hi> to <hi>See;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And <hi>Princes</hi> will my <hi>Lordly Rivals</hi> be.</l>
            <p>With so much esteem they spoke of her; they render'd her so much Justice, that I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most jealous of them. They curs'd the Province, that reclusely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:179501:78"/>a Genius as delicate as any at the Court: And People will not easily believe, that at Fifteen Years and an half one can know so much. You know, what inclinations I have to that amiable Person; You are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with her: So, do not be jealous, if I make my Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to her. I know I have been always too indifferent to you, for your having the least regret for losing such an Heart as mine: The incomparable D .... has accepted on't, inspiring it with a Passion, that will never have an end but with my Life. I at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend her News with such an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, as is unknown to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Hearts. She knows, I am lodg'd at ..... I was reduc'd to the greatest despair, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting without being able to bid her, <hi>Adieu:</hi> But there was no help for it. Besides, it show'd, as
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:179501:78"/>if she car'd very little, that a Man shou'd take leave of her, which she but too freely and unconcernedly gave me. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you, to let me understand some of her News, since you refuse to let me hear yours. I have ventured this Letter by <hi>Madam</hi> ........ An Answer by <hi>Saturday,</hi> I entreat you, and to believe, that I am both yours and <hi>Madamoiselles</hi> D ......</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Most humble Servitor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>IRIS,</hi> her Answer to <hi>TIMANDER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Four and Twentieth Letter.</head>
            <p>IN reality, <hi>Sir,</hi> I did already reckon you amongst my revolted Lovers. Your sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Retreat contain'd the whole
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:179501:79"/>System of a Revolt. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, I am told here, that you love me; but forasmuch as you your self do not tell me so, who have more Interest in the Thing, I know not how to believe it. Good God, to go without bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding me, <hi>Adieu!</hi> This is the utmost, that the most desperate or most indifferent Blade in the World cou'd do. Thanks to my Eyes, you are not the first! And, thanks to what those very Eyes have procuc'd in your Heart, you believe, you ought not to be the second! For (to deal sincerely with you) I observe a certain Air of Boldness and Confidence in your Letter, which does in no wise please me. You speak of your Passion, as if it was necessarily to suppose mine: And to use my free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of speech, I think you some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what too adventurous, for an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Lover. How do you know,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:179501:79"/>but that believing you lost, I have laid out for some new Lover, or, whether during this pretended In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terregnum, I have been always Mistris of my own Heart? This is a business, subject to Caution: Your calm and easie way with you is very unseasonable at a time, when every true Lover ought to dread something. Do you think your absence more fatal to my Repose, than ever your presence has been, and that what ordinarily destroys the best founded Passion, has given a Being to mine? I wish, you were somewhat more alarm'd, that I might be in an estate to secure you in the Conclusion, and to tell you rather than you shou'd tell your self, that I am still free, and by consequence in a Condition to engage my self. I have an hundred odd things to tell you on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: But I have not leisure to dwell on it, as doubting, that you have
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:179501:80"/>expected my Answer these three or four days.</p>
            <p>I did not receive your Letter till yesterday: And, as it was appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently open'd before I had it, and I shall be oblig'd to adjust things with <hi>Madam</hi> ....... you must look for some asperities upon this point. Your imprudence and indiscretion do very well deserve them: And I think, you manage very ill the glory of <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> D ..... who bears too great a Relation and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy with me, not to be taken for my self. Lay your measures bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter together another time: If you had stay'd here but two days more, I would have taken the way of ..... which I look upon to be more sure and Commodious. Thither you may direct your Letters every <hi>Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> and I will send for 'em by very faithful hands: And you shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive mine every <hi>Tuesday. Adieu:</hi> Let me have your Avisos, with all the Galantry at <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="letter">
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:179501:80"/>
            <head>The Five and Twentieth Letter.</head>
            <p>IF I had made a less Revolt from Reason, I had, unquestionably, made a greater from Love: And I ought to have departed (many thanks to your disdains) not the most desperate but the most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different of all Men. The harsh and rough manner, wherewith you left me, might reasonably Authorize mine: Yet however, do you call to mind, with what an Air I bid you, <hi>Adieu,</hi> and with what an Air you receiv'd it? But no matter for that: I am afraid, such a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance may let you know, that I went away much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate than indifferent. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this, I do all that lies in my power to become so: And if (as you say) I take upon me a certain confident way in my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which is not to your Palate, I am sure, in your Papers you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:179501:81"/>retain a certain indifferent one, that is not at all to mine. If you think me somewhat too bold for an absent Lover, I dare tell you in my turn, that I think you some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to bold for an absent Mistris: For, if my presence has not been fatal to your Repose, are not you afraid, least this plain acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will restore me all mine, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing absence, according to your Philosophy, doth frequently kill the best formed affections? Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your Maxims, if I am to fear a Rival in your Heart, have not you also some reason to fear a Rivalless in mine? By your Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, it would be sufficiently w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted, to meditate Treachery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unfaithfulness: For, upon the whole compute, do you think, that the Pleasures and Charms of <hi>Paris</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not blot out my mind the horrours and cruelties of .... believe me, <hi>Paris</hi> is a taking City.</p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:179501:81"/>
            <l>There a thousand deadly <hi>crafty</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Baits</hi> are laid t' <hi>ensnare</hi> our <hi>safety:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>A <hi>thousand</hi> Foes! There's <hi>Youth,</hi> there's <hi>Beauty,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>There's <hi>Dress, Fringe-petticoat,</hi> and <hi>shoe-tie.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>There's <hi>Wit,</hi> and <hi>Nice Politeness</hi> too,</l>
            <l>And <hi>that,</hi> or <hi>nothing</hi> sure must <hi>do.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>'Tis <hi>true,</hi> we <hi>need</hi> not thither <hi>roam;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>You, <hi>Iris,</hi> have <hi>all these</hi> at <hi>home,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yet <hi>unoblig'd</hi> to <hi>Tyring-room.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But yet, there's <hi>one</hi> thing; you have <hi>not,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of <hi>gentle Passion</hi> not a <hi>jot.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>I fancy, the last ought to give you more alarms, than all the rest, And, if you may be uneasie upon account of Wit and Merit, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not remain so well satisfi'd, as to point of Tenderness and Affection; for that every Mistris, of your fierceness and indifference, ought to fear the kindness and tractable manners of some more human Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valless. I must confess to you honestly, when I see you have so little Passion, that I would choak and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e mine, and I could wish
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:179501:82"/>to be in a Condition to tell you with as much ease and Tranquillity as you tell me, that I am still free, and that you may engage me; but that you are fully assured of your own power, and the weakness of my Heart, and you have little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to fear the loss of it. What delight, now, shou'd I take in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>settling you, if you were somewhat fearful of me? But, herein, you have but too much reason, to have an unshaken good opinion of your self, which is founded upon your own Merit. But, notwithstanding this, ever since my coming to <hi>Paris,</hi> I have done all that lay in my power, not to think of you so often, by making my Addresses to one of the sinest Women in <hi>France,</hi> who doth certainly carry more good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture than you do, about her.</p>
            <l>Yet, <hi>handsom</hi> though she <hi>be,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Tho she has no <hi>Cruelty,</hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:179501:82"/>
            <l>Tut <hi>unrebuking</hi> takes th' <hi>Address,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>I should have <hi>more Love,</hi> not <hi>more Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Than herewith, I cannot make a better ending: This is enough to you. <hi>Adieu.</hi> I expect your News.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="letter">
            <head>From <hi>TIMANDER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Six and Twentieth Letter.</head>
            <p>I Am come from <hi>Versailles,</hi> where I have been three days. At my return, I find no Letters from you: I stay'd till <hi>Tuesday,</hi> as you promis'd me. I am in a doubtful perplexity, whether you have receiv'd mine by the way of ..... Draw me out of this inquietude, if you please, and with the soonest you can. I write now to you in great hast, the Post<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hour coming instantly on. If I were as well satisfi'd with you, as
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:179501:83"/>I am with ..... I should be most happy. I am made much on here, by a thousand Courtesies, but I cannot wring one from you: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I adore you, and think of nothing else: This is enough. An answer I beg of you: I believe the way of ...... most secure. I have yet no answer from <hi>Madam....</hi> I cannot find much honour in her procedure, if she has open'd the Letter, I directed to her for you. She may write to me, when she pleases; but I will not send her the <hi>Airs</hi> of <hi>Dambruis,</hi> till she makes me an answer. I am horribly vex'd, that the Minutes are so urgent: But, do what I will, I must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with assuring you, that I am everlastingly <hi>yours.</hi> I desire an answer, as soon as you have receiv'd mine: For, I do not much matter, whether it be <hi>Tuesday</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any other day, seeing you know my direction, which is very safe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="letter">
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:179501:83"/>
            <head>The young <hi>IRIS</hi> to <hi>TIMANDER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Seven and Twentieth Letter.</head>
            <p>SEveral Lovers I have had; but never in my Life did I see such a sincere one as you. As 'tis apparent you lov'd me for having seen me, I might well doubt, that you would not Love, when you saw me no more, and my single Idea cou'd never stand firm and good against all those gay Persons, you view every day. Never did Lover, before, confide in her, that might cause his Torment, those pleasures he meets withal elsewhere in her absence. To tell you the righteous truth of things, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call back again the integrity of the first Ages: And, if you have not the constancy of those not so much
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:179501:84"/>antient as Antick times, at least you have their sincerity. This is, likewise, a Vertue; and you have pitch'd upon it to the other's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice. But, why did you not consult me? You should have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen the first. Upon the word of a Christian, I am very much scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daliz'd at your way of proceeding: I think, I shou'd have lik'd much better a Vice, that was somewhat more Complaisant, than so disobli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging a Vertue. I cannot tell, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it's your Freedom or your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constancy, that displeases me the most: I tell my self, that 'tis the Confession, which offends me, but in truth, I will not peremptorily decide, whether it be the Word, or the Thing: You may draw, what Conclusions you will from this. But, to consider things more closely, this pretended Infidelity I do sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be a Lover's cheat and trick, that is more faithful, than
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:179501:84"/>he wou'd be thought to be: For, when we leave People in the lurch, we do not use to advertize them of it, we let our selves bend to our own declentions, and are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>custom'd to frame such refined Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logisms. I fancy, you had a mind to try, whether I wou'd be sensible of your loss: In this case, I forgive you with all my Heart. But, what do you design by making Jealousie precede Passion in my Heart? Why shou'd you go about to raise such a Sentiment there, when it is so sweet, to inspire it with those that are most delicate. Would you have me begin to have a sense of Love by all, that it hath most cruel and bloudy-minded? No, instead of taming and rendring me meek and tractable with it, you put me into Arms and Battel-array a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it. You manage your Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests with no great Policy, and Old <hi>Nick</hi> of <hi>Florence</hi> is no such well-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to you: For,</p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:179501:85"/>
            <l>In a <hi>fine Mold</hi> Love only does <hi>appear,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Concealing,</hi> what gives <hi>Jealousie</hi> or <hi>Fear:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And, we should <hi>keep</hi> our <hi>Properties</hi> by <hi>Law,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>If we an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> sway <hi>fore-saw.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>In effect, Jealousie [as I have heard say] has such motions, as are too sharp and Netlish: It ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther provoketh and irritates, than softneth and asswages the Soul: So that instead of making me taste the pleasures and kindnesses and (as I may say) the Clemency of Love, you will allow me presently nothing but its vexation and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terness. This same Stratagem would never have bore me far; I should have immediately im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach'd the Enterprize. Love has much more pretty and acceptable ways, to insinuate himself into the Heart: For, what will that, which you have taken, get you, but these following Verses?</p>
            <lg n="1">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:179501:85"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of a</hi> Sequester'd <hi>Shepherdess</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You</hi> fear <hi>to be a</hi> Lover;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By</hi> change <hi>of whom for</hi> something, <hi>that hath</hi> less</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Severity, you would</hi> remove <hi>her.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh! do</hi> not <hi>make a</hi> separation</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of</hi> one <hi>Heart between</hi> Two;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But the</hi> last <hi>Conqueror</hi> pursue:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For it's more</hi> Natural, <hi>to maintain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Heavenly <hi>Blessings of a</hi> peaceful <hi>Reign,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Than</hi> choose <hi>black</hi> War, Fire, <hi>Sword and</hi> Desolation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>This <hi>you may</hi> do <hi>by my</hi> consent;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And I shall nought</hi> Gain-say:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Only one Quest.</hi> What by your fear is meant,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I ve</hi> Catechis'd <hi>mine</hi> Heart <hi>to</hi> Day.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grateful</hi> alarms <hi>suit well a</hi> Passion,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When</hi> tost <hi>by</hi> Sighs <hi>and</hi> Tears,</l>
               <l>Expos'd <hi>each Moment, to</hi> new Fears,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But</hi> now, <hi>I can</hi> spy <hi>no</hi> pretence,</l>
               <l>Timander, <hi>for this pretty</hi> fearing Sense:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis</hi> stupifi'd <hi>in a</hi> dead Inclination.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:86"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 5. Lin. 23. <hi>for</hi> member, <hi>read</hi> number. p. 13. l. 19 <hi>r.</hi> inaccessible. p. 21. l. 19. <hi>r.</hi> Bulky. p. 24. l. 9. <hi>for</hi> should <hi>r.</hi> would. p. 30. l. 17. <hi>for</hi> do <hi>r.</hi> does. p. 38 l. 5. <hi>for</hi> would <hi>r.</hi> should. p. 40. l. 19. <hi>r.</hi> snudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. p. 42. l. 18. <hi>r.</hi> ridiculous. p. 45. l. 4. <hi>r.</hi> through. <hi>ibid. r.</hi> brought't. p. 62. l. 7. <hi>r.</hi> alass p. 97. l. 11. <hi>for</hi> of <hi>r.</hi> at. p. 102. l. 9. <hi>for</hi> to <hi>r.</hi> two. p. 111. l. 12. <hi>r.</hi> repent. p. 118. l. 3. <hi>r.</hi> amusement. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 18. <hi>for</hi> make <hi>r.</hi> take. p. 191. l. 5. <hi>for</hi> it, <hi>r.</hi> not. p. 130. l. 7. <hi>r. Genius.</hi> p. 135. l. 21. <hi>r.</hi> consters. p. 137. l. 1. <hi>r.</hi> insupportably. <hi>The</hi> Reader <hi>is desir'd to</hi> mend <hi>or</hi> excuse <hi>the</hi> Faults <hi>in</hi> Pointing.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:86"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:87"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179501:87"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>